sleep and study don't forget to
subscribe
in this lecture I'm going to introduce
the fundamentals of operating systems
what they are what they do and why
they're important now what's an
operating system
well it's a layer of software that
provides two important services to a
computer system
it provides abstraction and arbitration
abstraction means hiding the details of
different Hardware configurations so
that each application doesn't have to be
tailored for each possible device that
might be present on a system arbitration
means that the operating system manages
access to shared hardware resources so
that multiple applications can run on
the same Hardware at the same time
without interfering with one another at
least Hardware resources that need to be
managed include the CPU
hierarchy of memory all the input output
devices on the system and to some degree
the power and system management features
in the system
many of these features are handled
directly by the hardware but the
operating system is involved
particularly in energy conservation now
the abstraction features of the
operating system allow Hardware devices
manufactured by different manufacturers
to have
the same interface
within software for applications to use
these Hardware devices all have
different low-level instruction sets
they all have particularly particular
capabilities features and details that
are unique to each Hardware device
if we didn't have a common interface
into these Hardware devices first of all
our variety of Hardware might be limited
but worse every application on the
system would have to be programmed to
use every single device on the system
an example back in the 1990s computer
games often required internal
programming for specific video cards and
specific sound cards it was often
necessary to go into the settings for
each game and tell the game what type of
video card you had what type of sound
card you had for the purpose of
configuring the game to use that
particular Hardware
imagine if that had to be done for every
single application on the system
including say a calculator or a web
browser that would be very untenable
situation in terms of being able to make
use of computers the way we use them
today
also what if we could only run one
program at a time on a computer system
years and years ago that was the case
however a modern system is running
multiple applications simultaneously
and it's up to the operating system to
ensure that all these applications can
access resources so each CPU is divided
among the different programs each
program gets access to memory
input output as well as disk and in an
Ideal World the operating system also
enforces policies that isolate
applications from each other so that a
crash in one application doesn't take
down the entire system or other
applications
now
of these examples do we have a situation
where we have abstraction or arbitration
well first example supporting both Intel
and AMD processors
this is an example of abstraction
we don't have to write separate software
for an Intel processor
relative to an AMD processor at least
for 99.99 of applications
simply write the application once it
will run on either process
switching between applications is an
example of arbitrating Hardware
resources among the different
applications on the system
separating memory allocated to different
applications is also an arbitration
activity it keeps one application when
overwriting the contents of memory that
being used by another application
enabling video conferencing software to
use different camera devices
this would be an example of abstraction
the video conferencing program just has
to know how to use a camera interface
that the operating system provides and
then different cameras from different
manufacturers can be used
without having to write the application
the video conferencing program to be
able to talk to each individual camera
similarly accessing two different hard
disks from two different manufacturers
any underlying detail differences
between those drives can be handled by
using the operating system to abstract
away the details
sending and receiving messages over a
network is both abstraction and
arbitration on the one hand we're
abstracting away the details of each
particular network card to be able to
send and receive the message on the
other hand we're sharing that network
card among all the different
applications on the system
now we can think of the system in terms
of layers
at the bottom of the layer cake we have
the hardware
this is what executes the software the
top three layers
the operating system is the middleman so
to speak between the applications and
the libraries and utilities upon which
the applications Depend and the
underlying Hardware
specifically the core of the operating
system or the kernel so named after say
a kernel of corn
is the minimum piece of software that's
needed to share the hardware between the
different applications
whatever lives outside the kernel that
is software is said to be in user space
that means it's application code or
sometimes even parts of the operating
system that are not strictly necessary
to share the hardware or abstract away
its details
now operating systems Implement a common
mechanism for allowing applications to
access the hardware which is abstraction
and the applications make requests from
the operating system to go and access
the hardware or other features by making
system calls down into the operating
system this is called entering the
operating system or iterating entering
the kernel from the top path
operating systems are also able to alert
applications that Hardware has changed
perhaps a network packet has come in
perhaps the user has pressed a key on
the keyboard
these alerts
are delivered via system called
interrupts and refer to entering the
kernel from the bottom half from the
hardware side of the operating system
we should also note that operating
systems can manage and terminate
applications by sending signals to those
applications
now there are a wide variety of
operating systems out there they
basically fall into two categories
Microsoft Windows which is not Unix and
everything else which is UNIX
Microsoft Windows systems non-unic
systems are the most popular desktop
operating systems at the moment
however they're rapidly being eclipsed
by tablet devices most of which are
running Unix style systems Windows is
typically pre-installed by PC
manufacturers which accounts for a good
portion of its present popularity
Unix systems on the other hand are
installed by the end user except for
commercial Unix systems and Mac OS 10.
Mac OS 10 is probably the best selling
Unix system of date and Linux which
includes the Android platform
is probably second
now there are some Mainframe systems out
there also some of which are Unix like
some use custom operating systems there
are a variety of players in the embedded
systems Market however that's presently
dominated by Android with Apple's IOS
which is based on Mac OS 10 in close
second
others
Symbian Blackberry OS tiny os are
confined to smaller markets
now the idea behind the Unix systems
began with a time sharing system started
in 1964 called multix and the idea
behind maltics was to make Computing
into a remote service that could be
accessed by terminals using telephone
lines it wasn't terribly successful
because dial-up connections of the time
at about 9 600 baud were rather slow
however Canada actually did have a
multic system deployed and used to this
part of their National Defense Network
until the year 2000.
maltix has remembered however primarily
for its influence as a multi-user shared
system
and today with cloud computing there's
some significant parallels between some
of the cloud computing models that we
used and some of the ideas that were
pioneered back in the multic system
now Unix was actually a play on the term
multix
it was developed by Bell labs in 1969
it's actually a trademark term so some
authors use starnics to refer to the
family of systems and use the word Unix
only for the commercial distributions
the original Unix systems were
commercial distributions with free
variance BSD and Linux coming along late
80s and early 90s
now Unix systems are time sharing
systems in that they support multiple
users at the same time but they're
designed to be run on local Computer
Resources instead of remote resources
the Berkeley system distribution which
is based on at T's commercial
distribution was one of the first open
source BS one of the first open source
unit systems to emerge it was based on
the commercial distribution so at T sued
UC Berkeley but an eventual settlement
allowed Berkeley to distribute BSD
freely in both source and binary form
today's descendants of BSD include
FreeBSD openbsd and Mac OS 10 which is
based on the Unix vsd system
Linux however was an alternate approach
to getting a Unix light kernel running
on computer system this was started by
Linus torvales as an undergrad at the
University of Helsinki released in
source code forum in 1991 and often
combined with a set of user space
utilities and libraries created by the
gnu project thus the resulting
combination is sometimes called the news
Linux
it has been commercially successful for
many device classes including web
servers Network and embedded devices and
mobile phones
some people including myself use Linux
as a desktop platform and it does have
benefit of having the one kernel that's
scalable from embedded devices all the
way up to supercomputers
now it's convenient to think of a system
computer system as a set of layers
where the top layer we have a group of
applications these are the programs that
we run and with which we interact on a
day-to-day basis to accomplish various
tasks
these applications are built on top of
libraries and utilities some of which
are included with the operating system
and some of which are installed
separately
the operating system acts as an
intermediary layer between the
application layer and the utilities and
the underlying Hardware the underlying
Hardware consists of several important
pieces I'll talk more in detail about
these in a moment
two primary pieces that come to mind are
the central processing unit which
actually executes the program
instructions and the memory hierarchy
which provides a place to store
instructions and data for use in
computation
now the memory hierarchy is critical to
understand because the speeds of each
level of memory within the hierarchy
vary
the fastest memory consists of CPU
registers and then the cache attached to
the CPU itself
whereas the slowest memory consists of
persistent memory typically disk the
hardware also includes a bunch of input
output devices you have a keyboard mouse
network interface card screen printer
plenty of others webcam different types
of devices
one of the other things that the
hardware does is supplies power to the
system via power supply and removes heat
generated by the system through cooling
this is typically done through fans
built into the computer's case now when
we look at a computer system from the
outside we see something called a form
factor now form factor is simply a set
of specifications for standard sizes of
equipment to allow different computer
components developed by different people
be interchanged with one another in
standard form factors include ATX which
is a typical workstation size form
factor Micro ATX and Mini ITX which are
used in small form factor systems such
as bookshelf systems and home theater
PCS and rack mount systems which are
typical servers in the data center
now laptop systems are a special case
these types of systems typically are
proprietary in nature the extent it's
not easy to take components out of one
laptop and put it in another laptop
workstation systems however do allow
easy component interchange
and these are the simplest of systems
they typically support multiple users
but normally only one user at a time
when a workstation is shared between
different users it often involves a user
getting up from the keyboard and another
user sitting down of course it's not
always the case but generally that's the
case
workstation systems are also frequently
either ATX or microatx form factors and
each workstation typically has its own
power supply which can be an issue of
efficiency considering the power
supplies are only about 65 to 85 percent
efficient workstations can be used to
host server applications this is
particularly true in smaller settings
such as small businesses non-profit
organizations
server applications in larger scale
environments such as Enterprise
environments are typically hosted in
rack mount systems and racknon systems
are simply a space efficient way to put
a whole lot of servers into one data
center rack mount systems are measured
or rack sizes are measured in terms of
units or u in a typical racks 42 Utah so
the most space efficient of servers a
one-use system with 12 cores in each
machine could enable up to 480 cores 480
CPU cores to be supported by a single
rack however there won't be much room
for expansion there won't be much room
for extra devices or extra hard drives
for that setup we use 2u and 4u systems
which are less space efficient but do
allow for more expansion more discs to
be included and more add-in guards now
if we take a computer system and we open
up the case inside we're going to find a
power supply
we're going to find a motherboard or
what Apple calls a logic board and
attached to that motherboard we're going
to find the CPU we're going to find
Random Access Memory we're going to find
expansion slots for add-in devices some
of which may be populated and we're
going to find that the motherboard
contains its own on-board devices such
as Network controllers or video
controllers inside the case we're also
going to find persistent storage devices
such as hard disks solid state drives
and Optical drives and here's a
conceptual view of what the inside of
the computer system looks like here we
have the motherboard which has some
expansion slots these are normally used
for add-in cards to be plugged in to add
functionality to the system onboard
devices which are soldered onto the
motherboard and are not removed one or
more CPUs which are typically removable
these are typically separate chips and
each of these chips inside you can't see
them but inside are typically multiple
CPU cores and some kind of cache memory
random access memory is another type of
memory that's attached directly to the
motherboard and it's typically in the
form of removable modules connected to
the motherboard via cables we find a
hard disk optical drive perhaps a solid
state drive the central processing unit
is the part of the computer that
actually executes instructions has one
or more execution cores most modern CPUs
have at least two cores CPU registers
are used for direct computation direct
operations that are occurring right now
the cache is used to store program
instructions and data that will be used
immediately the next few instructions
that are going to be executed this cache
is divided into levels of different
speeds it's also volatile it loses
contents whenever power is disconnected
and it's expensive this type of fast
memory is quite expensive random access
memory is separate from the CPU this is
used to store programs and data
while the program is in a state of
execution
this memory is order of magnitude
several orders of magnitude faster than
hard disks or even solid state drives
which is why programs are loaded into
random access memory by the loader
before they start executing most
programs also buffer their data in RAM
for Speed
however the memory and RAM is still
volatile and it contents are lost
whenever power is disconnected and it is
more expensive per unit storage than
disk space or even solid state drive
space persistent storage is the slowest
of all types of memory in the system
this is non-volatile storage for data to
be saved whenever the system is powered
off
now this is the least expensive type of
storage per unit of capacity
but it is slow it's not fast enough to
execute programs directly largely
because the CPU would constantly be
waiting on the drive to give it the next
instruction and that would slow down the
CPU hard disk drives are what we
typically think of when we think of slow
persistent storage these are mechanical
devices that use magnetic storage
basically a magnetic medium on top of
either a glass or metal disc called a
platter
and multiple platters that are stacked
spin at high speed with the heads moving
back and forth between tracks on the
platters
accessing data on a hard drive is thus
subject to two types of delay
seek time which is the time required to
move the heads back and forth and
rotational delay which is the time
required for the platter to rotate
around to the location the desired data
is stored
now hard drives are relatively
inexpensive per unit of storage space
but they are mechanical which means
they're guaranteed to fail sooner or
later
here's a diagram of a hard disk and here
we can see the platters which are
stacked on top of each other and spun
around by a motor motor spins us around
at high speeds
the head moves back and forth now
there's typically one head first side of
each bladder so the heads are actually
stacked up
and a Servo motor moves the heads back
and forth
the time it takes to move the head from
the inside of the platter to the outside
of the platter or from the outside back
to the inside to get the appropriate
track on the platter where data is
located is called the seek time
the time it takes for the spot where the
data is located to rotate around under
the head is called the rotational delay
so if I have a piece of data right here
about where the mouse pointer is
my drive is rotating clockwise
the head has to seek to the track where
that data is going to be located
and I have to wait for that data
come all the way around
and wind up under the head so that it
can be red
this adds to delay in accessing reading
or writing data from the hard drive so
in performance critical situations we'll
typically use solid state drives these
drives have no moving Parts they instead
use solid state chips to store data
consequently they have no seek time no
rotational delay and faster burst
transfers
much higher performance than hard drives
however this performance comes at a cost
and solid state drives themselves will
eventually fail each block of an SSD can
only be written the finite number of
times before it wears out
the drive itself extends its own
Lifetime by reallocating blocks
dynamically
so that each block is written in average
number of times instead of a large
number of times this process is called
where lovely it extends the life the
device significantly given that our
persistent storage devices are
guaranteed to fail in time it is
critical system administrators keep
backup copies of programs and data so
that the system can be restored after a
failure
now the backup media should be stored
separately from the computer center
itself best practice is on-site at least
10 miles away in a location that can be
protected from damage as well as theft
or loss of data backup media include
Optical disks such as reportable CDs
DVDs or Blu-ray
these Optical discs are nice because
they're inexpensive however they do
degrade over time scientists are still
working on the details of exactly how
long but it is known that data will
become unreadable eventually
flash drives such as USB sticks are also
inexpensive although a bit more
expensive than DVD media
they're slow sometimes slower than DVD
media and they themselves will lose data
eventually due to electrical properties
inside the flash memory tape drives are
considered best Enterprise level
solution which of course means they have
the highest costs but they have the best
reliability on average despite being
somewhat slow to access for reading and
writing cloud storage is another option
for many users and in this model
backups are simply uploaded to a remote
server that someone else maintains
typically a backup service provider
cloud storage is relatively low cost and
convenient however its speed does depend
upon the internet connection that you're
using to send data to or retrieve data
from the backup service and theft of
data can be a concern the operating
system implements a common mechanism for
allowing applications to access and
share Hardware the applications can make
requests from the operating system via
system calls the operating system can
deliver Hardware events to applications
and this is how we allow our
applications to make use of the
underlying Hardware of the computer
system I'll be discussing disk input
output
And discussing many of the physical
properties that come into play when
attempting to schedule a hard disk drive
for Access by multiple programs in
particular I'll talk about disk
attachment
talk about some of the properties of
magnetic disks discuss disk addressing
discuss partitioning and introduce
solid-state drives but begin with disk
attachment
disks are attached to the motherboard
via some kind of cable and the exact
type of cable depends upon the bus in
use on the system
there are several different types of bus
which are implemented by different chips
attached to the motherboard on the
different computer systems one common
bus that was widely in use until the
early 2000s on consumer grade Hardware
was the integrated Drive Electronics or
IDE bus this has been since acronymed
parallel ATA or Pata
it consisted of 40 to 80 ribbon cable
connecting to a 40-pin connector to
provide 40 simultaneous parallel
channels of communication between the
motherboard and the hard drive
Enterprise level systems of that time
period typically used scuzzy or small
computer system interface buses which
consisted of the cabling of 50 to 80 pin
connectors between the hard disk and the
motherboard scuzzy also defined a
standard set of commands a standard
protocol for interfacing with disks CDs
and other types of storage devices this
protocol was useful for recordable CD
media and dvd-rom media
and was implemented on the ATA bus using
the scuzzy protocol
in a system known as a tapi or ATA
packet interface now in minor times
serial interfaces between the
motherboard and the disk have replaced
for the most part the parallel
interfaces
for ath style disks we have Serial ATA
or SATA which replaces the 40-pin
connector with a seven pin connector
still uses the same protocol either ATA
or a chappy protocol
and serial attached scuzzy or SAS which
uses the scuzzy protocol over a narrower
Channel consisting of 26 to 32 pins
both of these new serial attachment
mechanisms support higher bus transfer
speeds enabling theoretically faster
devices to be attached to the
motherboard it does not necessarily mean
however the disks have gotten that much
faster we still store large amounts of
information using magnetic disks these
are metallic or glass platters that are
coated in a magnetic surface
and a stack of these platters is rotated
at high speed by an electric motor a
stack of heads moves back and forth
across the platters altering the
magnetic fields in order to read and
write data
moving the heads back and forth results
in seek time and waiting for the platter
to rotate around to the correct position
results in rotational delay historically
magnetic media were addressed by
geometry the smallest addressable unit
of space on a hard disk is called a
sector this is typically 512 bytes at
least on older disks though other sizes
have been used and newer drives go up to
four kilobytes
tracks are circular paths in a constant
radius from the center of the disc and
each track is divided into sectors one
head reads from a single track on a
single side of each platter when you
stack multiple heads up while using
multiple tracks on the various sides of
several different platters the result is
what's called a cylinder and
historically accessing disks required
accessing the particular data locations
using cylinder head sector or CHS
geometry address as disks grew larger
and faster however this type of
addressing scheme became Limited
and so logical block addressing was put
into use and it's now the standard today
logical block addressing or LBA gives
each block on a disk its own logical
address and leaves it up to the disk
firmware to convert The Logical
addresses into physical locations on the
disk
current standards with logical block
addressing on ATA will allow enough
space for disks up to 128 heavy bytes
operating systems normally Implement
these 48-bit addresses using 64-bit data
structures
thus operating systems that support
64-bit disk addressing can generally
support hard disks up to eight zebi
bytes of data assuming we're using 512
byte sector sizes now regardless of the
size of the disk it is convenient to
partition the disk into multiple
sections so that we can isolate data
from each other we can isolate the main
partition of the operating system from a
partition we would use for swapping out
pages of virtual memory for example and
we can isolate that from user data
also with early hard drives it was
convenient to isolate partitions so as
to minimize seat Time by making it such
that the head didn't have to move as far
in order to access data now there are
two types of partition tables or data
structure that resides on the disk to
indicate where on the disk the different
partitions lie a common partition table
type that's in widespread use today is
is the master boot record-based
partitioning scheme
and the way this works is that the BIOS
on the system the basic input output
system actually loads the first 512 byte
sector from the boot drive at boot time
and code stored in that 512 byte sector
loads the rest of the system
also within that sector is stored the
partition table which is called a Dos
style partition table
in the Dos partition table still uses
Legacy cylinder head sector addressing
supports a maximum of four primary
partitions one of which can be an
extended partition with logical drives
in it
and supports maximum partition sizes and
maximum partition starting addresses at
two tebi bytes
this is the default partitioning scheme
for Microsoft Windows and most Linux
distributions however as hard drives
become larger and grow past two
terabytes the good partition table or
GPT starts to be used
this is a larger partition table that
can support distance or partitions up to
eight zebi bytes in size
for compatibility with old partitioning
tools to prevent old tools from
overwriting sections of the disk and
seeing in his free space a protective or
dummy Master boot record is retained at
the beginning of the disk
GPT is the default partitioning scheme
in Mac OS 10 is an optional partitioning
scheme in Linux
and is supported in 64-bit versions of
Windows 7 Windows Vista and Windows
Server 2008 provided that the system
uses the extensible firmware interface
or EFI instead of the Legacy BIOS
interface
for Linux the grub2 bootloader can use a
Legacy BIOS interface but it requires a
dedicated small partition on the hard
drive in which to store the rest of the
bootloader hard drives and magnetic
media are used for large quantities of
space because of their relative low cost
when high performance is required we
prefer to use solid state drives or ssds
these drives have no moving Parts which
makes them generally faster and less
subject to physical damage than
mechanical hard disks
most of these ssds use nand flash memory
to store data
and this is a storage mechanism that's
based on injecting or removing an
electron from a flash cell
injecting an electron into a flash cell
changes its state from one to zero so
this is backwards from what one would
expect an empty flash cell actually has
a state of one instead of zero
the membranes through which this eject
this electron is injected and removed
eventually wear out typically after
anywhere from a hundred thousand to a
million Cycles
furthermore the electrons tend to leak
out over long time periods periods of
many years causing flash to lose data
which makes flash based memory systems
unsuitable for long-term backups in this
diagram we can see how a flash or how a
solid state drive using flash memory
works
blank flash memory stores the value one
one one one one one one one one so we
have all ones here
if I want to write the value one zero
zero one zero one zero zero
I have to pop electrons into the second
third fifth seventh and eighth flash
locations the eight those bit locations
I'm I'm pretending we only have a byte
here if later I wish to change that
stored value to one zero one zero zero
zero one one I must first erase that
block of flash memory before I can
program the new data value generally I
must erase flash memory in the size of
an erased block and this is typically
four kilobytes waiting for this block
Erasure procedure causes something
called right amplification where
successive writes to an SSD become
progressively slower to avoid this
problem typically erase the SSD ahead of
time whenever space has been freed on it
and there's an ATA command called trim
that facilitates this process one other
issue that has to be dealt with with
ssds is the fact that each cell can only
be written to and read from or generally
written to erased and written to a fixed
number of times this is typically
between a hundred thousand and a million
so to spread out the rights across the
entire SSD the SSD moves data around the
drive as files are updated and it also
reserves a certain amount of free space
unused so that that free space can be
swapped in and out with space that's in
use later this process called wear
leveling has the advantage of
dramatically increasing the useful life
of the SSD and reducing write
amplification whenever clean blocks are
made available however in order for the
right amplification reduction to be
effective the operating system and the
underlying file system must support the
ATA trim command and furthermore it's
impossible to ensure that the disk is
secure against forensic data recovery
because it may not be possible to
overwrite and properly erase the
reserved cells of memory that have been
taken out of service thus a used
solid-state drive should be physically
destroyed instead of attempting to
resell it which can be an issue because
a solid-state drive has a higher upfront
cost so in summary disks are attached to
the system via some kind of bus the
newer bus styles are SATA and SAS these
modern discs are addressed using logical
block addressing they're partitioned
either with DOs partition tables or good
partition tables GPT use will increase
as the size of disks becomes larger
owing to the limits of the Dos partition
table and solid-state drives offer
higher performance at a higher initial
cost subject to the requirement of wear
leveling and subject to not being able
to be safely resold due to the inability
to forensically secure the data on the
drive in this lecture I'll be discussing
disk scheduling I'll be introducing the
purpose of disk scheduling talking about
some classical and historical disk
scheduling algorithms talking about
Native command queuing and disk
schedulers that are currently in use in
the Linux kernel and then I'll talk a
little bit about how I O requests can be
efficiently scheduled on solid state
drives scheduling serves two purposes
disk scheduling serves two purposes the
first of these is to arbitrate disk
access among different programs
this ensures that competing programs
have access to disk resources and that a
single program cannot monopolize the
disk resources in such a way as to
prevent other programs from accessing
the disk with mechanical hard drives
scheduling algorithms historically have
also attempted to improve disk
performance by reducing the number of
seeks required moving reducing the
number of times the drive head needs to
be moved if the drive head has to be
moved too many times a lot of throughput
can be lost from the disk because we're
waiting on all the seek times to occur
the simplest scheduling algorithm would
be the first come first serve algorithm
which is implemented in Linux as a no op
scheduler this algorithm is extremely
straightforward it simply consists of a
fifo cube into which new requests are
added the requests are removed from the
queue in order one by one these requests
are sent to the disk for processing now
there's no reordering of the queue this
is a first come first serve ordering so
back-to-back requests for different
parts of the disk may cause the drive
head to move back and forth across the
platters wasting quite a bit of time the
seeks historically several attempts have
been made to try to improve this
Behavior one example would be the scan
algorithm or the elevator algorithm and
in this algorithm the drive head only
Moves In One Direction it serves all the
requests in that direction before moving
back in the other direction this is
called the elevator algorithm because
it's modeled after how an elevator Works
in a building the elevator leaves the
ground floor moves to the highest floor
stopping along the way to add passengers
traveling up remove passengers at
whichever floor they wish to stop on and
then once the algorithm reaches or once
the elevator reaches the highest floor
turns around and comes back down same
process here in this example with the
scan algorithm assuming that the head
starts at sector one and this request
for sector 50 comes in while sector 61
is being processed the algorithm is
going to process the requests in order
3 12 32 40 42 61 84 97 and since that
request for sector 50 came in while 61
was being processed that request for
sector 50 is going to have to wait until
the head changes Direction and returns
to sector 50. now there are a few
optimizations of the simple scan
algorithm the original algorithm
proposed that the head would move all
the way from the beginning of the disc
to the end of the disk and then all the
way back to the beginning the look
algorithm improves upon this Behavior by
moving the head only as far as the
highest number of requests before
changing directions and moving it back
down the circular versions of the
algorithm see scan and C look only serve
requests moving in One Direction so for
example with circular scan the head
would start at the first sector move all
the way to the end of the disk servicing
requests and then come all the way back
down to the first sector without
servicing any requests and start the
process over again these are historical
algorithms in the sense that with modern
drives we have LBA or logical block
addressing and so we don't actually know
where the disk is placing data
physically this type of algorithm was
used historically with cylinder head
sector addressing where we knew the
physical properties of the disk and the
idea here was to reduce average seek
time
at no time did we know where the platter
was that was up to the disk to figure
out so there was no way to reduce
rotational delay only minimize seektow
another algorithm and attempts to
minimize seek time is the shortest seek
time first algorithm or sstf
this algorithm actually orders requests
by sector location
so when the request for sector 50 comes
in it's kept in an ordered queue a
priority queue
and the next request to be served by the
disk these requests are still sent out
one at a time
is chosen by looking at whatever request
is closest to the correct disk position
historically this could result in
Starvation because if a bunch of
requests come in for one piece of the
disk requests for the remainder of the
disk might not be processed for lengthy
periods of time furthermore once again
with logical block addressing the
operating system doesn't really know
where the sectors are laid out on disk
and so this algorithm doesn't really
work with modern hard drives
also a solid state drives this algorithm
assumes there's a disk head which in the
case of a non-mechanical drive there is
not in the Linux kernel an approximation
to shortest seek time first was
implemented with the anticipatory
scheduler
this was the default scheduler from
2.6.0 to 2.6.17 it was removed in 2.6.33
because it's obsolete
the idea behind the anticipatory
scheduler was to approximate short of
seek time first
by ordering only the read requests into
an ordered queue into a priority queue
if the next read request was close to
the current head position that request
would be dispatched immediately
otherwise the schedule would actually
wait a few milliseconds to see if
another request arrives for nearby
location
and starvation was avoided in this
algorithm by placing expiration times on
each request and adding preemption so
that if a request was waiting too long
it would go ahead and be serviced
regardless of its location
the idea here was to reduce overall
seeking
there is a separate cue for write
requests because right requests could be
performed asynchronously we did not have
to wait on those requests to be
completed before our process could
continue doing useful work
this algorithm was shown with low
performance drives to improve
performance on web server applications
however it was shown to have poor
performance for database loads where
there were a lot of random reads and
writes on the disk and with high
performance disks this algorithm
actually breaks down modern hard disks
generally do qualify as high performance
disks the reason being is that they
Implement something called native
command queuing this is a feature of
newer SATA drives and basically native
command queuing leaves scheduling of
disk requests up to the disk itself the
disk circuitry and firmware makes the
decision about which request to handle
next
to do this the disk has a built-in
priority queue of about 32 entries
and the disk is able to schedule its
requests automatically taking into
account both the seat time and the
rotational delay since the disk knows
the location of the platter
this makes modern discs much more
efficient and this works with logical
block addressing the operating system's
role with this type of hard disk is
really more arbitration of the just
resources among the different programs
running on the system one modern Linux
scheduler that can be used for such
arbitration is called the deadline
scheduler
and in this scheduler the kernel
maintains separate request cues for both
read requests and write requests similar
to the anticipatory scheduler reads are
prioritized over writes because
processes typically block or stop and
wait while waiting to read something
from the disk
thus rights can be done later at some
point when it's convenient for the
operating system
the waiting time in each queue with the
deadline scheduler is used to determine
which request will be scheduled next
a 500 millisecond request time is the
goal for read request this is the time
it would take to start the request
with a five second goal to start a write
requests
this scheduler May improve system
responsiveness during periods of heavy
disk i o at the expense of data
throughput since each request has a
deadline and the longer request has been
waiting the sooner it will be scheduled
this is especially useful for database
workloads because there are many
requests for different parts of the disk
however for web servers and other
services that try to access large
quantities of data located in the same
location in the disk this particular
scheduler can actually reduce total
throughput completely fair queuing is a
somewhat different idea
where instead of actually scheduling the
i o requests
the completely Fair queuing model
schedules processes or running programs
to have time slice access to each disk
and essentially this cfq scheduler gives
each process an i o time slice and that
process can do as much i o on the disk
as it would like within that time slice
when the time slice expires the CF key
scheduler moves on to the next process
and gives it access time to the disk
there is a little bit of similarity here
to anticipatory scheduling since a
process can send another request during
its time slice and try to get that
request in without having a lot of seek
time
however this algorithm can waste time if
a process does not immediately turn
around and send another request
thus it can reduce the overall disk
throughput since there could be idle
times while waiting to see if another
request will come in for our time slice
expires this has been the default
scheduler in Linux since 2.6.18 for
solid state disks we have to choose a
scheduler that accounts for the fact
that there's no seek time to worry about
on the disk
the anticipatory scheduler the elevator
algorithms short of seek time first
all of these algorithms can actually
reduce performance on a solid state
drive because they make assumptions
about minimizing head seek time and we
have no heads to move with a solid-state
disk completely Fair queuing can also
reduce disk performance because of
idling at the end of a Time slice that's
true for any disk so what do we do to
maximize performance for solid state
drive
there are really two good choices for a
solid state drive there is the NOAA or
fifo scheduler this works well for
general purpose systems however when
their handy I O workloads and we want to
maintain system responsiveness the
deadline algorithm is useful since other
processes will have more opportunities
to access the disk in summary operating
systems are arbitrating disk access
among different processes to prevent one
process from monopolizing the disk and
preventing other processes and having
access
on older discs with cylinder head sector
addressing the operating system was also
attempting to reduce seek time thus
improving aggregate disk performance
however newer sanatists with Native
command queuing scheduled themselves to
reduce both seek time and rotational
delay
thus
algorithms that attempt to minimize seek
time are unnecessary
Furthermore with solid-state drives
scheduling mechanisms that are based on
Old mechanical assumptions can actually
reduce performance so for ssds we're
really only interested in arbitration
this lecture I'm going to discuss
development Cycles in particular we'll
talk about software life cycle steps in
software development
talk about some software development
models and give a brief overview of
formal methods the software life cycle
is a way of expressing how software
comes into being and evolves over a
lengthy period of time there's more to
software development than simply
programming
in particular we need to plan the piece
of software that we're going to develop
when we're talking about a new piece of
software
figure out what the requirements of that
software is going to be
design that software to satisfy those
requirements
and then perform several rounds of
coding and testing to ensure that our
finished application actually meets the
requirements before we can put the
application into production
the life of a software application is
not over however simply because it
enters production
over time invariably we will find the
need to upgrade the software which means
going through the same development
process all over again
and since any software application less
trivial than hello world contains bugs
we will have quite a bit of ongoing
maintenance in order to find and fix
errors that creep up in the software
we'll also need to support users and go
through several of these processes
before the software finally gets to the
point where it has reached its end of
life and is replaced by a new
application software development
activities comprise a number of steps
we have to conceptualize the type of
software that we're going to be creating
perform requirements analysis to figure
out what the software actually needs to
do
come up with a design for the particular
application that we wish to implement
and then finally Implement and test the
application
during the maintenance phase of software
life cycle
we need to check and fix bugs
it's important that we be able to
replicate bugs that are reported to the
from the user so that we're able to
verify the bugs do in fact exist and
determine the actual location of the
problem before trying to implement a fix
once a fix is implemented it too needs
to be tested before a patch can be
released for the software now managing
these development activities is an
important step in and of itself
each step of this process requires some
kind of orchestration particularly as
the size of the development team
increases
a discipline process helps to maximize
Effectiveness when the work is being
done by more than one person in the
details of this process management are
what we call a development model the
simplest development model is the code
and fix model
this is really the simplest of models
because it exhibits a complete lack of
any kind of design discipline what
happens is programmers simply sit down
write some code maybe run a couple tests
fix the code based upon the tests
deliver the result to the customer
if the customer likes the code then
they're done if not then go back fix the
code some more deliver it again this
process continues until the customer is
either satisfied or just completely
gives up
this type of model is inefficient
the code is often hastily completed
quite a few bugs this type of model is
while fairly well suited to outsourced
programming is not really suitable for
long-term support of a particular
application because the project is
treated as something that's to be coded
and later forgotten the opposite extreme
would be the waterfall model which is an
attempt to follow a conceptual diagram
of processes step by step and perform
each step all the way to completion
before moving on to the next step
so one would start with a concept
perform requirements analysis until all
the requirements were teased out perform
a design step until the complete design
was finished
and then start the coding this model
doesn't work well in practice because
often issues related to requirements do
not emerge until after a few versions of
the software have been completed and the
user comes back and fills in the
development team on details that weren't
previously disclosed during the original
requirements analysis phase similarly
the design often needs to be changed as
the source code evolves
there is a related model called The V
model that tries to establish
relationships between these steps
however these models are generally not
considered effective iterative and
incremental models are the most popular
software development models used today
and instead of Performing each task to
completion like one would try to do in
the waterfall model and break the
project into pieces and Implement one
piece at a time
test and deliver multiple prototypes
during the project development phase and
solicit feedback from the customer for
each given prototype this process begins
with a concept but then goes through a
requirements analysis a partial design a
prototype and testing in this feedback
process multiple times and over time the
software application from its
requirements through its design through
its code are progressively revised until
the application actually satisfies the
customer's requirements once this occurs
some final testing and integration steps
can be performed before the software is
finally released and put into production
now there are multiple iterative and
incremental development models rapid
application development is a model that
features short planning phase with a
large number of prototypes Agile
development puts a strong emphasis on
people and interactions over particular
requirements Dot documents and other
formalities and focuses on responding to
customer feedback and developing in a
more feedback Centric way extreme
programming is a form of Agile
development with extremely short
prototype release cycles and very little
documentation other than the application
itself for larger teams a more formal
approach is available with a Spyro model
which emphasizes risk analysis at each
step in order to evaluate the progress
of the project and attempt to prevent
cost overrents there is also a branch of
development called formal methods these
are used for life and safety critical
software systems and are in fact
required by the European Union for
avionics software and other safety
critical applications clean room
software engineering is a process in
which software is formally verified to
ensure that it meets all specifications
and is statistically tested and
statistically quality controlled to
ensure the application is actually
performing the tasks that it's supposed
to perform this is also an iterative and
incremental approach however it does
require much greater documentation of
the testing procedures so how much
formalism is actually required in a
software development process well Dr
Aleister Coburn came up with a scale
and determined that the need for formal
development processes increases with the
size of the development team the
financial risk of the project or the
safety critical nature of the final
system or any combination of those
factors furthermore depending on the
regulatory requirements in under which
the software is being developed there
may be a greater need for documentation
and process verification than in
regulatory domains where there is little
or no such regulation so in summary
software development encompasses much
more than simply writing program code
most of the popular development
processes that are in use today are
iterative and incremental approaches
that emphasize building small prototypes
and adding on to those prototypes as the
project progresses however safety
critical systems and
projects with extremely large
development teams or high risk often
will need greater formal procedures in
order to coordinate the development
process and may require formal verif in
this lecture I'm going to discuss file
systems
I'll be providing an overview of the
purpose of file systems discussing
metadata that they store
explaining how we create a file system
through a process known as formatting
talk about some issues with file systems
including fragmentation and journaling
briefly discuss some internal layouts
used by different file systems and
finally talk about mounting and
unmounting file systems to make them
available to users
the file system is responsible for
laying out data on a persistent storage
device and ensuring that data can be
retrieved reliably
the file system is an abstraction of
disk space it provides routines for
querying opening and closing files and
providing human readable names for files
and some kind of organizational
structure for files typically through
directories or folders
without a file system we would have to
access disk by physical location or by
address and each program would have to
reserve certain address limits for its
exclusive use
file systems in addition to performing
this abstraction also arbitrate disk
space among different programs and
different users of a computer system
file permissions allow users to have a
certain degree of privacy
while file quotas ensure that one user
does not monopolize the entire system by
utilizing all the disk space
file systems are also responsible for
storing metadata or information about
each file this includes a file name file
size
who owns the file what group that owner
belongs to what permissions exist for
each different category of users on the
system to access that file as well as to
provide certain time stamps on Unix we
have the inode creation time the file
modification time and optionally the
last file access time
metadata records also include internal
information that is important for the
file system itself such as pointers to
the actual data on disk and a reference
count for how many different names refer
to the same file system called hard
links
we create a file system by taking an
empty partition or a partition that
we're ready to reuse and formatting it
formatting quite simply is the process
of making a new file system on an
existing partition
formatting typically destroys the
structure of any file system that was
previously installed on the partition
thus when you format a partition you
lose the access to
its contents at least through standard
tools
however unless that free space unless
that partition is securely erased the
contents that were formally on the
partition can still be recovered using
forensic tools
the only safe way to switch between file
systems on a single partition is to back
the data that's our net partition up to
another disk
format the partition using whatever the
new file system would be and then
restoring the data from the backup there
is no safe way to change a file system
type in place without losing data
bus systems do suffer from a few issues
over time
sections of a file
in a file system can become
non-contiguous in other words a file
gets split over different parts of the
disk and in the process that also splits
up the free space so that when new files
need to be allocated they have to be
split up to take advantage of smaller
blocks of free space
this is a situation called fragmentation
it's worse in some file systems than
others
fragmented file systems were a big
problem with mechanical hard drives
simply because a fragmented file
requires a seek to move from the
location of the first fragment to the
location of the next fragment and
possibly further seeks if there are more
fragments
not so much a problem on solid state
drives however since there's no seek
time
and file systems can get around this
problem either with offline
defragmentation tools that the system
administrator can run manually or they
can use fragmentation avoidance
strategies or automatic on the Fly
defragmentation
another issue that can occur with file
systems is that a single high-level file
system operation typically requires
several low-level steps in order to
complete
if the computer Should Crash or power be
lost in the middle of those steps being
performed the file system could be left
in an inconsistent state
a solution to this problem is called
journaling and the way this works is by
recording all the steps that are to be
taken in something called the journal a
special part of disk space reserved for
this particular information
records all the steps that are going to
be taken prior to taking the steps
thus if the system should crash in the
middle of a file system high level
operation
all that needs to occurs the journal
simply needs to be replayed next time
the file system is mounted and the steps
can be carried out again and leave the
file system in a consistent state
internally file systems may use one of
several different approaches for storing
data on the disk
a simple layout is called the file
allocation table
which simply has a single table on each
partition to store metadata and the
addresses of data segments for each file
dial allocation table type storage
methods are limited only in terms of how
big the file allocation table can be
and these limitations specify among
other things the maximum size a file can
be and how many files can be on the
system
another approach is to use something
called inodes which are data structures
on Unix systems that contain the
metadata for a file including pointers
to the actual data
inodes do not store the file names
however these are stored in a separate
structure called a directory that Maps
file names to inodes
the maximum number of files of a single
file system can hold is limited by the
number of inodes created when the file
system is formatted this can be a
particular problem for file systems that
wind up storing a really large number of
very small files there could be plenty
of space left on the file system on the
partition however if the number of
inodes is exhausted then no more files
will be able to be created
another approach to storing files and
laying out data on the file system is
through the use of extents
extents support larger maximum file
sizes because they're designed to allow
files to be composed of several
non-contiguous blocks of space much like
fragmenting that could occur with a file
system that doesn't use extents
extent information is stored with the
metadata in the file inode or some other
type of data structure
for file systems that support extents
now regardless of how the file system
lays out its data internally we need to
make the file system available to users
and programs on the computer
to do this we perform a process called
mounting mounting is the act of making a
file system available to the users of
the system
the opposite process is called
unmounting which is disconnecting a
previously mounted file system
Unix systems Mount file systems at Mount
points which are simply directories
somewhere within the overall directory
structure of the system
so if I plug in a flash drive on a Linux
machine for example that flash drive may
be mounted at slash media my drive
I can mount a large number of different
file systems this way at the same time
and I can make all of the different file
systems appear to be part of One
Directory structure
on the other hand Windows systems use
Drive letters where the letter c is
reserved for the system partition the
one on which Windows is installed and a
and b are reserved for floppy drives
Windows supports a maximum of 26 file
systems to be mounted at once simply
because that's the number of letters
that are available to assigned drives to
its signed partitions
so in summary file systems organize data
store metadata provide an abstraction of
the underlying storage medium and
arbitrate access to the storage space
we create file systems through a process
known as formatting
we can make file systems more robust
against data loss during a power failure
through the use of journaling
internally file systems use various
different mechanisms for laying the data
out on disk but no matter how they work
internally we can make them available to
a running system by mounting them in
this lecture I'm going to discuss
requirements analysis
in particular I'll give an overview of
different types of projects
different types of resources that can be
applied to projects
talk about the purpose of Performing
requirements analysis
discuss stakeholders interests and
actors
and talk about the functional and
non-functional requirements of
development projects
software development projects can be
described as falling into a range in
between two extremes
at one extreme we have something called
a green field project
and it's called a Greenfield project
because it's analogous to building a
building on an empty field start with a
grassy field
build everything from scratch
it's a completely new system
get to make all the design decisions
from the ground up there's no existing
code that has to be merged into the
system
and this type of project has the
potential to be extremely rewarding to
the people who work on it
at the opposite extreme we have a
re-engineering project or a project that
needs to be re-engineered
this type of project begins with a pile
of existing code that lacks any type of
documentation whatsoever
the design of the system the
architecture of the system is an unknown
and in fact it's necessary to perform
code analysis to determine how the
application was designed and how it was
architected
this type of project is the greatest
potential for frustration
since many older programming paradigms
did not emphasize making code that was
easy to untangle
most projects fall in between these two
extremes
there are some projects that fall into
the Greenfield category there are some
re-engineering projects however many
projects are going to land in the middle
there's going to be some amount of code
that has to be reused yet there'll be
some amount of documentation at least
hopefully
now regardless of the type of project
we can utilize several different types
of resources in the software development
activities
of course we begin with people
we have a number of people who work with
us on a software development project we
have software Architects we have
designers we have developers we have
programmers we have others one other
type of person that I didn't put in the
slides but is important is someone
called a domain expert that's the type
of person who knows what types of
problems the software actually needs to
solve and what the business rules are
for that classic problem
of course we also have money
and infrastructure infrastructure
includes things such as computer
equipment software applications desktop
environments other computational
resources that we can utilize in order
to develop a working solution
of course given enough money we can
always purchase additional resources in
terms of additional infrastructure or
hire additional programmers Consultants
others to help with the process
now the purpose of performing a
requirements analysis is to make
effective use of these resources we have
available to us
ideally we'd like to keep our
development staff happy
we would like to spend our money wisely
and we'd like to optimize use of the
infrastructure
we have the aim of trying to determine
what exactly needs to be developed so
that we can build the right product so
that we can actually make something that
satisfies the business needs of whoever
has commissioned the product
speaking of folks who have an interest
in the product we can define a few roles
and relationships for specific
individuals within a software
development setting
one important class of individual is the
stakeholder
stakeholders are people or other
entities such as companies or groups
that have a vested interest in the
system under discussion it's often
called the sud
stakeholders include the customer the
development company itself
users of the system and other direct
participants in the system
however stakeholders may also include
indirect participants in the system
perhaps another agency or another unit
of the company is actually funding the
development work even though they may
not directly use the resulting products
these entities have vested interest in
the outcome of the system because they
have an investment in the system
now the interests that one could
associate with stakeholders are simply
the expectations that a stakeholder has
of the system under discussion
these interests may be of a technical
nature they could also be of a financial
nature or even a political nature
perhaps there's some aspect of the
system as some political significance to
someone
so interests fall into a variety of
categories
actors in a system are anything that has
Behavior
so this includes both human users and
other computer systems
the primary actor in a system is a
stakeholder that is using the system
directly to carry out some tasks in
other words this is the user who sits
down at the keyboard and actually runs
the application
in order to perform some business
function supporting actors on the other
hand are other entities upon which the
system or lies to complete a task
this could include something such as an
external database system an external
printing system some other functionality
that can be described as having
behaviors which the system requires in
order to perform its business functions
this could even be a person who has to
go and manually input some type of data
into the system
human actors typically require a user
interface or UI in order to interact the
system
computerized actors on the other hand
typically require something called an
application programming interface or API
in order to interact with the system
now when we're specifying requirements
and considering what type of actions an
actor can take with the system
we can divide the requirements into two
sets
the first set of requirements is called
functional requirements these
requirements specify what a software
application does
in other words given some set of inputs
this set of requirements should be able
to tell you what the outputs and side
effects of the system will be
for that set of inputs
this is the design of the software this
is the low level detail about how the
software responds to particular
different types of input
non-functional requirements on the other
hand specify what the software is these
are often called qualities of the
software an example of this is the
so-called herps list which includes
usability reliability performance and
Sportability
ISO or IEC 9126 also Define some other
qualities that a software system may
have including portability and
efficiency
non-functional requirements are embodied
in the architecture of the software how
is the software put together to meet
these quality requirements
so in summary
the types of development projects that
we could be considering vary from the
extremes of Greenfield to re-engineering
projects
these projects are supported by
resources including people money and
infrastructure
each project has stakeholders and each
stakeholder has interest in the system
stakeholders who use the system directly
become primary actors on the system
and software engineering requirements
can be classified as functional in other
words describing how the system works
what the system does or non-functional
describing qualities of the system or
what the system is in this lecture I'm
going to discuss features of the central
processing unit or CPU that are useful
for supporting multiple applications
sharing a computer system simultaneously
in particular I'll introduce
multi-programming and discuss the
hardware requirements to support
multi-programming
I'll discuss CPU privilege amounts x86
protection Rings mode switches and
briefly introduce interrupts
the first concept to introduce is
multi-programming in multi-programming
is simply the idea that we can run
multiple processes or multiple instances
of potentially several programs at the
same time
and we can do this by having the CPU
switch quickly among the different
processes enabling all of them to make
forward progress per unit of human
perceivable time
the CPU will switch quickly enough to
provide the illusion that all the
processes are running at the same time
even if we only have one processor core
in the vast majority of modern Computing
systems with the exception of some
special purpose systems are
multi-programming system
some of the old computer systems of the
day were batch systems that only ran one
sys one application at a time
now in order to support
multi-programming we have to have
certain features of our computer
hardware
first of these is an interrupt mechanism
for enabling preemption of running
processes whenever some kind of event
occurs we have to have a way of stopping
a process handling an event and then
restarting the process
we need to have a clock so that we know
how long the process has been running
and we need to have CPU protection
levels to restrict access to certain
instructions to prevent processes from
hijacking the system or just trying to
bypass the operating system altogether
we also need to restrict access to
memory in order to prevent reading and
writing to memory that a particular
process does not own belongs to somebody
else
two CPU protection levels are sufficient
a protected mode and a privileged mode
these modes are also called the
supervisor mode or kernel mode and user
mode
in kernel mode
all instructions on the CPU are enabled
and the kernel can access all memory on
the system
in user mode the CPU disables all the
privileged instructions and restricts
most direct memory operations thus a
user program must make a system call to
the operating system to request memory
or perform other resource allocation
tasks
in this way the user processes are
effectively sandboxed both from the
system and from each other
on the Intel based systems x86 and x8664
systems there are actually Four modes
available
these are implemented by what are known
as x86 protection Rings which consist of
four privileged levels numbered zero
through three
rating 0 has the greatest number of
privileges
code executing in ring 0 can execute any
instruction the CPU provides and can
access all memory
ring 3 has the fewest privileges all the
instructions are restricted to the set
of instructions that are relatively safe
in practice most operating systems
actually only use ring 0 and 3. os2 and
Zen are the notable exceptions that make
use of ring 1.
newer systems
with virtualization extensions either
the Intel VTX extensions or the amdb
extensions add an extra privilege level
below ring zero this is colloquially
sometimes referred to as ring negative
one
and this mode enables instructions that
allow multiple operating systems to
share the same processor these
instructions help
system support posting multiple virtual
machines at the same time
now regardless of the number of modes
available whenever we wish to change
modes for whatever reason we have to
perform something called a mode switch
and that occurs whenever the CPU
switches into user mode kernel mode or
hypervisor mode or whenever an x86 CPU
changes which protection ring is
presently effective
mode switches have the potential to be
slow operations compared to other
machine instructions depending upon the
hardware
a notable example was the first
generation of Intel Core 2 Series
processors in which the mode switches
into and out of hypervisor mode were
quite slow
one situation in which a mode switch
might occur is when something called an
interrupt happens
in an interrupt is simply a situation in
which the currently executing code is
interrupted so that an event can be
handled by the operating system
interrupts could fall into two
categories we can have involuntary
interrupts which are external to running
processes
these consist of things such as I O
interrupts which are generated every
time you press the key on the keyboard
or perform any other i o test
clock interrupts which are timer
mechanisms that can be scheduled to go
off at a particular time
and Page faults which have to do with
the virtual memory subsystem
interrupts can also be voluntary in
other words created by a process that's
running
system calls and exceptions such as said
fault or divide by zero actions can
result in interrupts as well
and the CPU provides Hardware mechanisms
for detecting when an interrupt is
occurring and handling the interrupt
so in summary multi-programming systems
allow multiple applications to run
simultaneously
implementing multi-programming reports
requires support from the hardware in
particular we need CPU privileges we
need a clock and we need some kind of
interrupt handling mechanism
CPUs used in multi-programming systems
need to have at least two privileged
modes Intel x86 Systems Support four or
five modes depending on the processor
mode switches can be expensive in terms
of performance so we don't want to do
them more than necessary and interrupts
enable Hardware events to be delivered
to applications and they allow
applications to yield control of the
system while waiting for events or
waiting for service in this lecture I'm
going to discuss kernel architectures
I'll begin by introducing the functions
of the kernel
explain the separation between mechanism
and policy
talk about some seminal early kernels in
the history of computing
and then introduce the differences
between monolithic kernels and micro
kernels
the kernel provides two functions the
same two functions is in the operating
system it provides abstraction and
arbitration
the kernel provides abstraction in the
sense that it provides a mechanism for
programs to access Hardware
a way to schedule multiple multiple
programs on the system
and it provides some method for
inter-process communication or IPC a way
for programs to send messages to each
other or send messages to Hardware
devices or out to the network
kernels also provide abstraction
mechanisms they ensure that a single
process or running program can't take
over the entire system
enforce any kind of security
requirements such as access privileges
that might be in place on the system
and they minimize the risk of a total
system Crash from a buggy application or
device driver
it's important to distinguish between
mechanism and policy when discussing the
internal components of an operating
system
the mechanism put simply is the software
methods that enable operations to be
carried out
an example of a mechanism would be code
that implemented inside a device driver
sends a message to a device that causes
that device to Blink a light enable a
camera or perform some other Hardware
level operation
policy on the other hand is a set of
software methods that enforce
permissions access roles or other limits
against applications so a policy for
example would be something that said
that only users who met certain criteria
could send a message out to a hardware
device to Blink a light or enable a
camera or perform some other Hardware
function
it's a generally accepted principle of
good design with mechanism and policy
should be separated as much as possible
an early kernel that separated mechanism
and policy quite well was the regna
centralin RC 4000 monitor kernel
this kernel was developed in 1969
primarily by Perry Brink Hanson for the
regna Central and rc4000 computer system
this was a computer system that was
developed in Denmark
and the central component of the system
was a small nucleus as brinkansen called
it called monitor
which allowed programs to send messages
to each other and allowed programs to
send and receive buffers which were
essentially types of messages for
Hardware to and from different Hardware
devices in particular at that time they
had a card reader a tape reader and a
printing style output device
other kernels with different scheduling
mechanisms and other capabilities could
be run under monitor in those days it
was not clear that multi-programming was
really a desirable feature for computing
thus someone could write a
multi-programming capable kernel and
actually run that as a sub kernel under
the monitor system
importantly this was also the first
system that allowed sub kernels and
systems level software to be written in
a high-level language in this case
Pascal
the system performance was actually
quite awful Brink Hansen stated that the
operating system itself was so slow at
performing its IPC tasks that there were
a number of issues with the system
completing tasks on time
however the system was stable and
reliable
making it successful in computer science
history even if it was not a successful
product commercially
on the other hand the opposite extreme
would be the Unix kernel this was
developed at Bell Labs by a team headed
by Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie also
starting in the late 1960s
the difference between the Unix kernel
and the rc4000 monitor was that the Unix
Kernel's design implemented performance
thus instead of having a very small
kernel that simply provided an IPC
mechanism and some basic resource
collision avoidance
this kernel actually provided all the
device drivers all the scheduling all
the memory management
including support for multi-programming
directly inside the kernel
this kernel was an early example of what
would later be called a monolithic
kernel a monolithic kernel is a kernel
that contains the entire operating
system in kernel space
runs all of the operating system code in
privileged mode or ring 0 on an x86
system
and divides the different functions of
the operating system into subsystems of
the kernel
all of these subsystems however are run
in the same memory space
this has the advantage of higher
performance
but the disadvantage is that the kernel
becomes less modular and more difficult
to maintain and the components are not
separated very well so a crash in one
component could in fact bring down the
entire system
the opposite of this the rc4000 style
kernel is what we now call a micro
kernel in a micro kernel basically
contains the bare minimum of code is
necessary in order to implement basic
addressing inter-process Communications
and scheduling
this basic amount of code runs in kernel
space and everything else runs in user
space
often with lower privileges
as a general rule of thumb micro kernels
contain less than 10 000 lines of code
micro kernel based operating systems
tend to be quite modular because they
divide the operating system functions
between the kernel and a set of servers
that run in user space
however because many of the core
functions of the operating system are
performed by user space components which
have to communicate with each other via
the kernel
performance does suffer
thus most kernels they're in use today
are a hybrid of these two designs
I'm going to introduce Murphy's Law of
reality sort of an extension of the
Murphy's laws with which you may be
familiar
and by definition of Murphy's Law of
reality is simply that reality is the
hazy space between the extremes of
competing academic theories in which
everything is wrong in some way at least
according to the theories
this idea of a hybrid kernel
architecture is a controversial one some
people do not like to use this
terminology at all
many people prefer to keep the binary
classification of Monolithic kernel and
micro kernel
however if we look at modern kernels
typically the monolithic versions of
modern kernels are broken into modules
that can be loaded and unloaded at
runtime this helps to increase
maintainability of the kernel
and true micro kernels today would have
unacceptable performance thus micro
kernel based systems typically have some
of the features of Monolithic kernels
such as more device drivers and other
code that runs inside the Kernel's
memory space
some examples of different types of
kernels for monolithic kernels in
addition to the system 5 units kernel
which is a descendant from the original
units kernel we have the Linux kernel
BSD MS-DOS and windows 9x kernels
Windows NT XP Vista and seven if you
don't prefer to use the hybrid
terminology would also qualify as
monolithic minerals and the Mac OS 10
kernel falls into the same category
terms of micro kernels the rc4000
monitor kernel would have been the
earliest however there have been plenty
other examples including mock L4 the MIT
exokernel project and the idea at least
behind the Windows NT kernel which was
based upon a micro kernel design the
same is true of the Mac OS 10 kernel
since that was originally based on the
mock micro kernel however those have
been heavily modified and now have many
properties of Monolithic kernels also
so in summary
the kernel is the minimum layer of
software inside the operating system
that provides the basic foundations for
abstracting away details of the hardware
and arbitrating between multiple
applications
when the bearer absolute bare minimum
implementations are used we call the
result a micro kernel
monolithic kernels on the other hand
have all their major OS components
contained within them
running everything inside kernel space
to improve performance
two early influential kernels were the
rc4000 monitor an example of a micro
kernel and the original Unix terminal
which was an example of a monolithic
kernel
in practice however most modern
operating system kernels are hybrids of
the two designs and have features of
both kernel type in this lecture I'm
going to introduce the unified modeling
language
uml
I'll be discussing software modeling
introduce uml
talk about some of its limitations
discuss a few of its diagram types
discuss the role of uml and software
engineering and mention a few case tools
in software systems especially complex
software systems it's useful to be able
to present a design to other Developers
for discussion during the development
process
complex software systems need to be
designed before they can be constructed
or modified anyway and it's helpful to
keep design documentation on hand so
that the system can be modified more
easily later
in order to communicate with other
developers and other stakeholders in the
system
it's helpful to have some analog to a
contractor's blueprint
consider for example in the real world
building a large building such as a
hospital
first an architect will come up with a
high level design for the project
Engineers will Design the individual
components and ensure that the hospital
will meet all codes and remain standing
and operational
and then during construction the designs
get updated slightly to account for
changes in any problems that are
encountered during the construction
phase
after construction the blueprints are
retained in case an addition is needed
later or in case modifications are
needed to the building
unified modeling language provides an
option for software Engineers to have
similar design documentation for
software projects
and in the early days of software
engineering diagrams were drawn using a
wide variety of different formats with
different symbols different connectors
different annotations and so forth
and developers moving between companies
or trying to collaborate across company
or even divisional boundaries within a
company had to be trained on each
specific format that was being used for
the communication
the idea behind unified modeling
language was to provide a single
standardized formatting in a
standardized set of symbols in order to
create a Common Language and the group
of folks that did this were Grady booch
Ivar Jacobson and Jim Rumba at rational
software corporation which was later
purchased by IBM
UMO was standardized by the object
Management Group
but the standards are not always
followed by uml tools and in particular
with the latest version of uml there is
no set of tests in order to verify tool
compliance with standards
however
uml has become popular for drawing
certain types of diagrams either
manually by hand using different tools
or using electronic tools
individuals drawing uml diagrams by hand
typically do not remain strictly
adherent to the standards there can be
slight variations in the diagrams as
drawn
the uml provides diagram types to model
system structure behavior and
interaction
there are some limitations to uml first
and foremost uml does not replace other
types of design documents a good example
of this is use cases
uml use case diagrams can provide useful
indexes into use cases however they do
not replace the use cases themselves
many of the diagram types that uml
provides are not actually used widely
simply because their specialty diagrams
that many developers don't choose to
utilize
uml diagramming tools often use
incompatible formats making them
difficult to Interchange diagrams
between one tool and another
in standardization of uml was a
controversial and in some circles
remains a controversial topic today
other software modeling approaches do
exist but were not included in uml
because they were not considered by the
uml authors
nevertheless uml does provide a rich
variety of diagram types
these can be classified into two to
three categories depending on how you
prefer to draw the classification
we have structural diagrams in
particular class diagrams that are
widely used to show how object-oriented
systems are designed
we have Behavior diagrams in particular
activity diagrams which can show how a
development process can be coordinated
and state machine diagrams which are
useful for representing finite State
machines that exist in many types of
software
there are also interaction diagrams
which can be thought of as a subset of
behavior diagrams and this can show how
different software components interact
with each other
uml as a tool when software engineering
is simply one of a number of tools that
can be used to plan architect and design
software applications
diagrams using uml are convenient for
communication between different members
of a development team
and they help communicate the
architecture and design of an
implemented Software System to Future
developers who might need to maintain
that system
there are some tools available called
case tools or computer-aided software
engineering tools that can take uml
diagrams a bit further and actually
generate Partial Program code from the
uml diagram
so if you have a uml diagram laying out
a few classes the case tools can often
fill in templates of the classes and
programmers would only need to fill in
the code for each individual method in
the class
other tools exist that can actually take
existing code and extract euml diagram
from that code showing how the code is
structured
so in summary uml provides us a common
set of communication tools for
presenting And discussing aspects of the
architecture and design of software
systems
uml is one of many tools used by
software engineers and software
applications exist for drawing uml
diagrams
and potentially generating code from
those diagrams
however these tools are often not
interoperable with each other in this
lecture I'm going to discuss uml
activity diagrams
uml activity diagrams are used for
modeling processes
these processes can include different
operations within software
they can include the software
development process itself
can also include business processes and
other types of process
in this example graphic I have a uml
activity diagram illustrating the
development for a simple client server
project
in which the client and the server are
implemented by different members of the
development team
the basic parts of the uml activity
diagram
include the initial State the final
state
and set of transitions in other states
and controls in between the initial
State and the final state
the initial state is represented by a
filled Circle
and represents the point at which we
enter the process
the final state is displayed as a filled
Circle within another Circle and this is
the state in which we exit the process
in between these two states we have
action States and activity States
action States represent single
operations in the process being modeled
and these operations are not broken down
into another activity diagram
activity States represent longer running
processes that occur as steps in our
outer process
and these inner processes have their own
activity diagrams to explain how they
function
within an activity diagram we can make a
decision to perform one step or another
or even repeat a prior step based upon
some condition in a uml activity diagram
this decision is called a sequential
branch and it's represented by a small
diamond borrowed from flowcharting
symbols
a decision can be taken at the point of
the diamond
and then transitions leading from the
diamond will indicate the next state
conditions associated with those
transitions are included in square
brackets as annotations next to the
transition error
the special annotation else indicates a
path to take if no other condition is
satisfied
in modeling processes it's useful to
show where certain steps can be carried
out by different people or different
components of the system in parallel
we can represent this in a uml activity
diagram by means of something called a
concurrent Fork
a concurrent Fork is simply a thick line
to which a transition connects and
several transitions originate
from the originating transitions we have
states that are reached in parallel
presumably by different entities within
the system
thus the concurrent Fork allows our
process to be split into multiple
concurrent paths things that can be done
at the same time and then we can get
back together later
in the way we come back together from a
concurrent Fork is with the opposite a
concurrent join this is the same kind of
heavy line
however transition arrows come into the
line and a single transition comes out
of the line to the next state in the
sequential process
so we have multiple concurrent parallel
paths meeting to form a single
sequential path
it's useful with concurrent forks and
concurrent joints to have something
called activity partitions or Swim Lanes
these are ways of annotating the diagram
to show which component individual or
entity is responsible for each parallel
path in the project
in this example we can see that the
entire team performs research and then
performs a design step
then we have a concurrent Fork after
which Bob implements the client and Jill
implements the server
after those implementations are done we
have a concurrent join and come back to
the team
separation of responsibility is
indicated by drawing a box or activity
partition around those parts of the path
that are the responsibility of one
single component one single team member
or one single entity
I'll take just a moment to talk about
types of tools we can use to draw uml
activity diagrams
a simple way is to draw the diagrams by
hand on paper
if we need a digital copy we can simply
use a camera such as the type of camera
in your cell phone to make a digital
image
some more professional looking results
can be obtained by using a drawing
program I've used Google Docs drawing
tool to make the examples in these
lecture slides however you could use
OpenOffice draw Vizio or another type of
drawing program in order to make these
diagrams
there are also some open source tools
that have uml-specific additions that
can be useful for making uml diagrams
these include DIA
certain plugins to the eclipse framework
however these are complicated to set up
and sometimes difficult to use
and umbrella which is a general purpose
computer-aided software engineering tool
so in summary
uml activity diagrams allow us to model
a process
this process can fall into any one of
several domains this could be a process
inside software this could be a business
process this could even be the software
development process itself how the
individual team members are going to
come together in the project
in this example I am modeling a software
development process a very simple one
you can see the initial State the filled
circle at the top at which the
development process begins
this process begins with the entire team
performing research
research is an activity state so it
would be described by a separate
activity diagram which I have not shown
after the research phase we would move
to the design phase in which the entire
team would be working on the design for
the software
after the design state which is an
action state so it's not further
Illustrated anywhere else
we have a concurrent Fork at which point
Bob goes and implements the client part
of the project and Jill goes and
implements the server part of the
project
when both Bob and Jill are finished with
their implementations we have a
concurrent join at which point the
entire team reassembles to integrate the
project and test the project
if all the tests pass we move on to the
ship state
however if the tests are not passing if
we take the else branch of that
sequential Branch then we go back to the
test step
finally once we've moved to the ship
state
we can move to the final state of the
diagram which indicates that this
process is complete
in this lecture I'm going to discuss
interrupts and device input output
when Hardware devices on a computer
produce events
we need some way of being able to handle
those events within the operating system
and deliver them to Applications
and Hardware devices are going to
produce events at times and in patterns
that we don't know about in advance for
example we don't know which Keys the
user is going to press on the keyboard
until the user actually presses those
keys
if a cat walks across the keyboard we're
going to see a completely different
pattern of key presses from which we
would expect to see with the human user
similarly if we have incoming Network
packets if we're running a server
application or even just a workstation
and we have messages coming in from the
network we don't know the order and
timing of those messages
we also don't know when the mouse is
going to be moved or when any other of a
whole bunch of Hardware events is going
to occur
so how can we get the information
generated by these events and make it
available to our applications for use
well we have two options
first option is that we can pull each
device we can ask each device if it has
any new information and retrieve that
information
or we can let the devices send a signal
whenever they have information and have
the operating system stop whatever it's
doing and pick up that information this
is called an interrupt
the polling model of input involves the
OS periodically polling each device for
information so every so often the CPU is
going to send a message to each Hardware
device in the system and say Hey you
have any data for me
and most of the time the device is going
to send back no don't really have any
data for you
other times the device is going to send
back some data
it's a really simple design
extremely simple to implement
but there are a number of problems with
polling
first problem is is that most of the
time when you're polling the devices are
not going to have any input data
delivered
thus polling is going to waste a whole
lot of CPU time
the second issue that occurs is high
latency if I press the key on the
keyboard that keystroke is not going to
get transmitted to the computer until
the next time the CPU pulls the keyboard
to ask which Keys have been pressed
if that
time is set to be really short I'll have
good responsiveness but the CPU is not
going to get any useful work done
on the other hand if we set that time
length to be long enough for the CPU to
get some work done there's going to be a
noticeable lag between the time I press
a key and the time a character appears
on the screen
since the device must wait for a polling
interval because it can translate input
we're going to have a high latency
situation
and again shortening that polling
interval to try to reduce the latency
simply wastes a whole lot of CPU time
checking devices that have no input
so better mechanism is to use a system
called interrupts and with interrupts
the hardware device is actually signal
the operating system whenever events
occur or more precisely they signal the
CPU and then it's up to the operating
system to receive and handle that signal
what the operating system will do is it
will preempt any running process in
other words it will switch what we call
context away from that running process
to handle the event basically it will
move the program counter of the CPU
to the code to handle that particular
interrupt
this allows for a more responsive system
than we could ever achieve through
polling without having to waste a whole
bunch of time asking idle devices for
data
however this does require a more complex
implementation and that implementation
complexity begins at the hardware level
specifically within the CPU we need to
have a mechanism for checking and
responding to interrupts
and this mechanism is implemented as
part of the cpu's fetch execute cycle
in the process of fetch execute the CPU
is going to fetch an instruction for
memory
increment the program counter
execute that instruction
but instead of Simply going back to the
next fetch the CPU actually has to have
additional Hardware to check to see if
an interrupt event is pending
if there is an interrupt pending then
the CPU has to be switched to Kernel
mode if it's running in user mode so the
privilege level needs to be escalated
save the program counter by pushing it
onto the stack
and load a program counter from fixed
memory location and that fixed memory
location is called the interrupt Vector
table or ivt
so we load the program counter from the
IBT and then the CPU goes and executes
that new instruction the next time the
fetch execute cycle resumes so the CPU
actually moves from executing program
code to executing code from the
interrupt Handler for the particular
event
if no interrupt is pending at the end of
an execute then we simply go back to the
next instruction fetch
the interrupt Vector table
consists of an array
of addresses of handlers
each element in this array essentially
gives the program counter location for
the Handler for a particular interrupt
this Handler is going to be in a
subsystem of the kernel for a monolithic
kernel or this Handler might invoke a
call to an external server for a micro
kernel
in any case however the first Handler by
convention element 0 of the array is
always the Handler for the clock
then handlers for different devices are
in the array after the clock Handler
so the interrupt Vector is always mapped
into the user part of memory it's always
available at all times so that the
kernel can go and look up interrupt
information whenever is necessary
an interrupt is processed by branching
the program counter to the interrupt
Handler
executing interrupt handling code
and then at the end of the interrupt
handling code there'll be an instruction
to return from the interrupt in the
Intel Assembly Language this is The
Irate instruction which loads the
process program counter back from memory
it pops the stack to get the original
program counter back
and goes ahead and changes the CPU back
to user mode so it removes the privilege
escalation
the interrupt handling mechanism is thus
able to handle events from Hardware
devices without having to poll each
device individually to get data in this
lecture I'll be discussing interrupt
controllers
in particular I'll introduce the old and
new mechanisms for delivering interrupts
from Hardware devices to the CPU
these methods include the original
programmable interrupt controllers and
the new Advanced programmable interrupt
controller with message signaled
interrupts
interrupt controllers provide an
interface for Hardware to Signal the CPU
whenever a device needs attention
it's important to note that this signal
only includes a message that essentially
says hey I'm a device I need attention
the CPU historically then actually does
have to go and pull the device to get
any data that the device may have
the older mechanism for performing this
operation was called a programmable
interrupt controller or pick
and it actually required dedicated lines
to be added to the motherboard
the ISA or industry standard
architecture bus Which dates back all
the way to the first PC back in 1987.
and older versions of the PCI or
peripheral component interconnect bus
utilized this mechanism
the new mechanism or the advanced
programmable interrupt controller is
used on PCI Express devices and some
newer PCI devices
now the old controller or the
programmable interrupt controller
actually consisted of two programmable
interrupt controller chips that were
attached to each other with one of the
chips being attached to the CPU
the so-called Master chip was the one
attached to the CPU
and pin 2 of that Master chip was
attached to a slave chip
each pin on each of the two chips allows
for 16 interrupt numbers to be created
interrupts 0 through 7 are correspond to
the pins of the master chip
and interrupts 8 through 15 correspond
to the pins of the slave chip now it
should be noted that since pin 2 of The
Master chip handles the slave chip
that the master programmable interrupt
controller only supports an effective
seven interrupts
so there are only 15 usable interrupt
Hardware lines for devices
and these are numbered 0 through 15 but
we have to skip the number two
now historically pin number zero which
corresponds in software terms to what we
call interrupt request line or irq0 was
connected to the timer
interrupt request line 1 was connected
to the keyboard
different Isa and PCI devices could then
use the remainder of the master chip by
connecting to irq lines three through
seven
on the slave chip pin 0 which
corresponds to irq8 was connected to the
real-time clock pin 4 corresponding to
irq12 was connected to a PS2 Mouse
pin 5 or irq13 connected to the math
coprocessor which was a separate
component from the main CPU in earlier
PCS
and then pin 6 and 7 corresponding to
irq lines 14 and 15 connected to the IDE
controllers these were used for disk and
eventually for optical devices
this left pins one through three on the
slave controller or irqs 9 through 11
available for Hardware devices
now these interrupt lines on the
motherboard were actually circuit traces
these were conductive paths
etched into the motherboard
that allowed interrupts to be received
from devices
there were 15 lines available of the 16
that could be used by devices with lines
0 and 1 reserved for the timer and a PS2
keyboard respectively actually even
before the PS2 reservation the original
at keyboard
Isa and PCI add-in devices actually had
to share interrupt request lines and
this sharing could lead to Hardware
conflicts that could lock up the system
it was thus up to the system owner to
manage the sharing by setting little
jumpers on the add-in cards so that the
cards were using different irq lines
there were also performance issues when
irq lines were shared because the
operating system actually had to pull
each device sharing an irq to determine
which device it was that raised the
interrupt polling was still necessary in
order to receive any kind of data from
the device regardless of whether it was
sharing an interrupt line or not
on Modern systems a completely different
interrupt mechanism is used
and this mechanism has a set of memory
registers on what's called an advanced
programmable interrupt control
in this set of memory registers is
connected to a single shared bus that
each device on the system can use to
raise an interrupt message by writing
that message into one of the memory
registers
these are called message signal
interrupts using the MSI and MSI X
specifications
essentially each device here I have a
timer RTC USB host controller SATA
controller is attached to the bus
and indicates its interest in raising an
interrupt to the apic by sending a
message over that bus
now this message does not contain any
data it's only a request for attention
if the CPU has to be involved in the
operation of sending or receiving
information then the CPU actually has to
contact the device in other words pull
it directly
there is a way around this called direct
memory access or dma transfers which are
used extensively on PCI Express devices
the register on the Apec stores the
request for attention until such time as
the operating system handles the
interrupt request and then that message
is cleared from the apic
this is the only interrupt mechanism
that's available on PCI Express buses
there are no Hardware interrupt lines
however a number of motherboards still
have interrupt lines physical interrupt
lines and have physical pick pens
so that they can support Legacy devices
your number of specialty Legacy devices
still in use that need to be supported
message signal interrupts do solve a
number of problems with interrupt
request sharing the original
specification allows each device to use
any one of 32 irq lines
the MSI X specification will allow each
device to use up to 2048 virtual lines
virtual interrupt request offers
essentially and this allows for Less
contention and reduces the need to share
interrupt request numbers by device thus
reduces the amount of time necessary for
the CPU to determine which device wanted
attention
so main thing to take away from this is
that the interrupt controller and the
interrupt request mechanism only allows
the device to raise a signal that says
it wants attention
it's up to the CPU or on certain buses
up the device and the memory controller
to get the information out of that
device and into memory in this lecture I
will introduce use cases
use cases are a type of requirements
document that provides narrative
descriptions of scenarios that will be
handled by the system
I will be discussing the elements that
make up a use case
these elements include the trigger
actors in The use case
preconditions steps in the process
described by the use case guarantees
made to the stakeholders and any quality
requirements applicable to the use kits
use cases are one type of requirements
document
they provide a written narrative that
describes how the system under
discussion or sud will behave in given
scenarios
after the system is implemented the sud
could be tested by following the use
cases and checking the behavior of the
system matches the requirements for the
given scenario
it is important to remember that a use
case is only one type of requirements
document
other types of requirements documents
such as the system conceptualization or
user interface specification do exist
the primary function of a use case is to
describe how the sud responds to
interaction from a stakeholder in the
system
in other words a use case specifies what
the set is to do in different scenarios
for example a use case for a database
system might specify what steps are to
be taken whenever the database
administrator asks to update a record in
the table on the other hand a use case
might specify that certain information
needs to be updated whenever a customer
makes a new order from a company
these two scenarios illustrate the
different levels at which use cases can
be written
at the high level we have business use
cases that describe the business process
that must be carried out
without specifying any details of the
system
these use cases are also sometimes
called essential use cases
lower level use cases or system use
cases describe how the sun will behave
in specific situations these use cases
incorporate details of the technology
being used
use cases may have either black box or
white box scope
all business use cases and many system
use cases use Black Box scope
this means they treat the system as a
mystery device
this specify how the system will behave
under given conditions but they leave
out all the details of how the behaviors
will be implemented
some system use cases on the other hand
may be written from a white box
perspective
the easiest cases detail some of the
internal operations of the sud such as
specific protocols or algorithms that
will be used
white box use cases are especially
useful for describing how different
components of the sud will interoperate
with each other
when writing use case narratives it is
customary to include a number of
standard pieces of information
the specific entries and the Order of
the entries will vary by organization
in most cases you will write use cases
by following a template
a sample use case template might contain
items such as the trigger for the East
case a list of actors involved in the
use case and a list of preconditions
that must be true before the East case
steps can begin
use case then specifies the system
behavior is a series of steps
illustrating how the primary actor
interacts with the sud
at the end of the scenario described by
the use case certain guarantees are made
to the stakeholders about the state of
the system
the use case might also specify quality
requirements such as the maximum amount
of time allowed to complete the scenario
in general a use case will have a
triggering condition
this trigger corresponds to the user
wishing to perform some action using the
sud
alternatively this trigger could be the
results of an event that occurs
somewhere in the system or outside the
system
preconditions are statements that are
assumed to be true when executing the
use case these conditions are not
checked anywhere in the use case
use cases guarantee that certain
conditions will be true at the end of a
process
these guarantees are promises made to
the stakeholder as to how the system
will behave
ideally the process would be successful
and the stud will deliver all guarantees
presented by the use case
however if an error or unexpected
condition occurs somewhere during the
process some minimal guarantees about
the state of the system should be given
actors in eu's case are external persons
systems or other entities that interact
with Assad in some way
these actors include the user or users
of the system any entities upon which
the system depends in order to carry out
a business function and any other
systems with which the sud interfaces
the actor that performs the actions in
the use case is called the primary actor
in a general sense the primary actor is
the user of the system that will be
created
thus by definition the primary actor is
also a stakeholder in the system
supporting actors have roles in carrying
out some operation of the system but
they do not utilize the system directly
in a business level use case the
supporting actors have important roles
in the business process but they do not
carry out the process directly
now use case documents are narrative
texts they tell a story about how the
system is going to act under given
scenarios
in order to communicate the story
effectively there are certain rows of
thumb that should be followed when
writing use cases
first use Simple language with active
voice and simple sentence constructs
for example say the user sits down at
the keyboard instead of
keyboard is presented to the user
second do not include user interface
elements in the use case
say the user enters data into the system
instead of the user types characters
into a text box in the middle of the
screen
leave the user interface designed
separate specifications or prototypes
finally every use case should end with
at least one guarantee about the state
of the system
if the process is successful how does
the system react
if the process fails what is the
condition of the system after the
failure
remember that computer software can and
does periodically fail
also remember that human users are
guaranteed to fail and that the system
should be made robust or as idiot proof
as possible
now you may be aware that the unified
modeling language provides a graphical
use case diagram
you may also believe that these diagrams
will save time compared to writing use
case narratives
unfortunately graphical use case
diagrams do not provide much information
about the process being described
they illustrate a stick figure
representing a primary actor
executing a use case
represented by a box containing the use
case title
however the graphical diagrams do not
provide any detail about the process
as such the diagrams are useful for
providing indexes into the use case
narratives but they do not add any real
value to the use cases themselves a
simple textual index with numbered use
cases would accomplish the same Purpose
with less effort
agile methods particularly extreme
programming have extremely short
iteration times that are not conducive
to formal use cases
one lightweight alternative to use cases
is the user story which is a short and
simple way of expressing a particular
requirement
user stories are written for each
scenario similar to the approach used in
use cases
however instead of a formal document the
user story simply expresses what a
primary actor would like to achieve in
the system
for example
a user story for a database
administrator might read
as a database administrator I want to be
able to perform an operation that
updates the name address and age fields
in a single transaction
user stories typically omit some design
details but these details can be
discovered later as the software is
developed
also these stories can be either black
box or white box in perspective
depending upon the needs of the
development team
in summary es cases describe a scenario
in which a primary actor interacts with
the system under discussion
each use case is named according to the
process it describes in use cases
generally have triggers indicating the
conditions under which the process is
applicable
use cases May specify preconditions
which are assumed to be true prior to
execution of the use case
use cases provide an outline of the
steps required in the process along with
a set of guarantees about the state of
the sud after the scenario is finished
quality requirements such as execution
time limits may also be specified
Agile development methods especially
extreme programming disfavor use cases
due to the time involved in creating the
documentation
the short iteration development
techniques use user stories and other
lightweight methods instead in this
lecture I'm going to discuss interrupt
handling
I'm going to begin by discussing
interrupt handling at the hardware level
and then move on to Features provided by
the CPU and finally features of the
operating system for handling interrupts
at the hardware level devices are
connected either via traces on the
motherboard or via a shared messaging
bus to the advanced programmable
interrupt controller
the CPU checks for Hardware interrupt
signals from this controller after each
user mode instruction is processed so
after each instruction is executed
running some particular program on the
system
the CPU actually checks to see if there
are any interrupts that need to be
processed
if an interrupt signal is present then a
kernel routine is called by the CPU in
order to handle this interrupt
the interrupt dispatch routine if it's
not implemented directly in Hardware is
actually a compact and fast routine that
could be implemented in the kernel often
coded in Assembly Language it has to be
that fast
the specific interrupt Handler is always
a kernel routine
or in the case of a micro kernel an
external server routine in this specific
Handler depends upon the type of
interrupt received these are typically
coded in C
so once again the fetch execute cycle we
check for an interrupt pending after
each instruction is executed
if there is an interrupt pending we
escalate privilege to Kernel mode
push the program counter onto the stack
in other words save it so we can resume
from that point in whatever program
we're interrupting
and then go and handle the interrupt we
do this by loading the program counter
the new program counter that is from a
fixed memory location provided to us by
the interrupt Vector table
the interrupt Vector table gives us the
address of all the different interrupt
handlers we need a separate Handler for
each type of interrupt the clock
requires different logic from the
keyboard for example other devices such
as say a webcam attached to your
computer needs different logic in order
to process messages from it so we have
different interrupt handlers for each of
these different devices
table simply stores the addresses of
each Handler and in our monolithic
kernel case the handlers are actually
part of the kernel and are mapped into
kernel memory space
the interrupt Vector table consists of a
list of each of these addresses for
kernel handles and conceptually is
mapped into both kernel memory and user
memory so that it can be accessed
quickly and historically these started
at address 0. however the mappings are
different depending on the architecture
on Intel based systems we have something
called the interrupt descriptor table
and the IDT provides special
instructions and data structures that
are actually managed by the CPU itself
so the interrupt handling can be as fast
as possible and protection rings can be
changed automatically
the IET is simply a reserved block of
RAM used by the CPU to jump quickly to a
specific interrupt Handler
this IDT is mapped into kernel space
which was originally beginning in
address zero but this mapping is
actually flexible with modern CPUs and
can be mapped into other parts of the
memory space
the first 32 entries of the IDT are
actually not used for interrupts per se
but they're actually used for CPU fault
handlers and then the interrupt Vector
table part of the data structure begins
after the CPU fault Handler table
when we actually go to handle interrupts
the handling occurs in the kernel and
this is done with two levels of
interrupt handling the fast interrupt
Handler and the slow interrupt Handler
the fast interrupt Handler is the piece
of code that's invoked directly from the
interrupt Vector table whenever an
interrupt occurs this is the piece of
code that the CPU is just going to jump
to when an interrupt occurs
fast handlers execute in real time and
they're called Fast interrupt handlers
because they need to be fast the
execution of one of these interrupt
handlers needs to be short
if any large-scale data transfer needs
to occur say we need to get a lot of
data from the device cell at once
this operation is handled by having the
fast interrupt Handler enqueue something
called a task into the operating systems
task queue
whenever all the fast interrupt handlers
for all the different interrupts are
done executing the CPU will go and check
the task queue and execute any tasks
that are present there
part of interrupt handling that goes
into the task queue is called slow
interrupt handling and it's called this
because it's not executed immediately
and it can be interrupted by other
devices
so what happens if an interrupt request
is received while we're still processing
an interrupt from a previous request
well there's no problem if we're in the
slow interrupt Handler because this
processing is done in such a way that we
can stop this processing and handle the
new interact if necessary what happens
if we are still running a fast interrupt
handle
well the new interrupt Handler could be
executed before the first interrupt
Handler is finished and this could cause
some major problems especially if we get
a new interrupt from a device that's
sharing the same interrupt line as the
one that we're handling
so what we do is we make fast interrupt
handling Atomic that is we make it
uninterruptable
on a single core system this is as
simple as disabling interrupts as long
as we're running a fast interrupt
Handler on multi-core systems their
actual special machine instructions to
facilitate Atomic operations that are
pegged to one CPU core
these Atomic interrupt handling
operations will run to completion
without interruption by any other
interrupt or any other request on the
system
thus the longer an interrupt Handler
takes to run the longer the system will
be unresponsive to any new interrupts
so what happens if a fast interrupt
Handler is coded in such a way that it
takes too long
other devices might be requesting
attention at the same time that this
long-running interrupt Handler is
executing
worse the same device that generated the
original interrupt might now have more
data to deliver to the OS before all the
previous data is completely received
this could cause Hardware failures
buffer overflows dropped data dropped
messages all kinds of issues at the
hardware level
however inside the operating system this
could lead to something called an
interrupt storm which is really bad
an interrupt storm occurs whenever
another interrupt is always waiting to
be processed whenever a fast interrupt
Handler finishes its execution
that could occur either because the fast
interrupt Handler is too long it needs
to be split into a fast and slow Handler
this can also occur if Hardware has
certain bugs that cause it to erase
spurious interrupts
if the operating system is perpetually
handling interrupts it never runs any
application code
thus it never appears to respond to any
user inputs
the result of the situation something
called a live lock the system is still
running it's still processing all these
interrupts however it's not doing any
useful work thus to the user the system
appears to be frozen
and when an interrupt storm occurs in
this live lock situation results the
typical way out of this problem involves
judicious use of the power button
so interrupt handling is an important
Concept in order to support
multi-programming systems
an interrupt handling when these
interrupt messages come through from
Hardware is divided into two types of
Handler so that we don't get the
interrupt storm
the fast interrupt Handler executes
atomically without being interrupted by
anything else but it must be fast must
enter that interrupt handler do some
very short operations and immediately
exit that handle if any long-running
operations need to occur as a result of
the device interrupt request we need to
handle those operations inside the slow
interrupt Handler
in this lecture I will discuss finite
State machines and uml state diagrams
uml State diagrams provide a way to
Model Behavior of a system by analyzing
how the state of the system changes in
response to input data
in this diagram we have a model of a
simple system that captures the user
entering a number consisting only of the
digits 0 through 9 and at most one
decimal point
the system finishes and presumably
Returns the inner number whenever the
user presses the enter key
invalid keystrokes are simply ignored
with the simple State machine such as
the one presented here we can verify
that the user has entered only numeric
data however understanding how the state
machine operates and how uml provides us
with the convenient way to draw the
state machine requires some explanation
First We Begin by observing that every
software system has something that we
call State
in simple terms Software State consists
of the current values of all the
variables in a program at any given
moment in time
in the case of object-oriented software
systems the state of the system is
stored within the objects in the system
and each object has its own state which
is stored in the object's variables or
fields
the essence of running a computer
program is changing the software from
one state to another
a computer at least as we know it today
is a machine capable of representing an
extremely large but finite number of
different states
computer programs simply move the
computer system from one state to
another state
a conceptual way to model a simple
computer or a single object in a
software system is to use a finite State
machine
finite State machines have a fixed
number of states and the system is
always in one of these states when it is
running
as computation progresses the finite
State machine transitions from one state
to the next
each state machine can receive input and
a state machine possibly produces output
during a state transition upon entering
a state upon leaving a state or even
within a state
for Simplicity the conceptual model used
for input and output data is a tape the
state machine can read characters from
or write characters to one of these
tapes
the set of characters that a machine
knows how to read or write is called an
alphabet
words are formed from this alphabet
creating a language that the state
machine recognizes
nearly all state machines have an input
tape
technically speaking a finite State
machine with only an input tape and no
output tape is called a finite State
automaton
this type of machine simply accepts or
rejects the input validating whether or
not it is a recognized word in the
language
a finite State transducer has two tapes
one for reading input and one for
writing output
State machines can be either
deterministic or non-deterministic
a deterministic finite State machine
transitions from its present state to
another state based solely upon present
State and the most recent input
character read from the input tape
in contrast a non-deterministic finite
State machine can transition from one
state to another on its own without
consuming any input data
these types of transitions are called
Lambda transitions or Epsilon
transitions in programming language
Theory
a state machine that produces output can
be limited to producing output only upon
entering a new state
this type of estate machine is known as
a war machine and is theoretically
easier to model
if a state machine can produce output at
any time within a state or during a
state transition it is called a melee
machine
by now you might be thinking that state
machines sound rather Limited in their
capabilities and this is a correct
observation for the simple finite State
machine
both deterministic and non-deterministic
finite State machines are equally
powerful but their power is limited to
recognizing inputs that could be
described using a regular expression
to obtain the power to process computer
programming languages which typically
utilize what are known as context-free
grammars we must add a stack to our
finite State machine to create a push
down automaton
alternatively if we modify a finite
State machine to be able to move back
and forth along a tape used for both
input and output we create a linearly
bounded automaton that can handle
context-sensitive languages as input
the linearly bounded automaton is the
closest theoretical State machine to the
present day computer the final type of
State machine is the turing machine
which further modifies the linearly
bounded automaton to make the tape
infinitely long giving it infinite
memory
such a machine if it existed could
handle recursively innumerable languages
the unified modeling language allows us
to diagram deterministic finite State
machines which allows us to model many
of the operations in individual objects
in a large-scale system perform
in the practice of writing software we
try to minimize non-determinism since
non-deterministic programs could produce
different results each time they are run
with the same inputs
therefore we would like our Enterprise
applications to be deterministic
uml State diagrams are used to model the
behavior of individual objects within
the system under discussion
one diagram is generally used for each
object being modeled so a normal set of
design documents would contain multiple
State diagrams
State machines expressed by uml either
can produce output at any time or the
designers can restrict the output to the
entry condition for each state
thus these State machines can use either
the melee or more model
I'm now going to illustrate the
components of the uml state diagram
first we have the initial state in the
final state of the system
these states represent the entry and
exit points for the diagram respectively
the initial state or diagram entry point
is represented by a filled Circle
the final state or diagram exit point is
represented by a filled Circle within
another Circle
internal States within the uml state
diagram are given by a rounded rectangle
divided into two sections
in the top section a human readable name
for the state is generally provided
this name should reflect the purpose of
the state
below the name the bottom section of the
state rectangle contains the set of
activities that the system performs
while in the listed state
these activities are specified by
providing a condition under which the
activity is performed followed by a
slash followed by the name of the action
that is to be executed
Three Special condition names are
reserved by the uml specification to
handle specific activities
these are entry which specifies an
action to take upon entering the state
exit which specifies an action to take
upon exiting the state
and do which specifies an action to take
while in the state
note that a do action may be a
continuous ongoing action that occurs
until the system leaves the state
transitions between states are drawn as
arrows originating from one state and
pointing to the next state
the system follows the arrows from state
to state until it reaches the final
state
a transition is taken only if the input
to the machine matches a trigger
condition specified next to the
transition error
this trigger condition can be
accompanied by an optional guard
expression enclosed in square brackets
in which case the transition will be
taken only if both the trigger matches
and the guard expression is true
after the trigger an optional guard
expression is placed a slash followed by
any action to take during the transition
the slash is always present in the uml
state diagram even if there is no action
given
uml does allow a state with any uml
state diagram to contain another state
diagram instead of a list of activities
these so-called nested State diagrams
are permitted but they will quickly make
a uml state diagram difficult to draw
and read
instead of nesting State diagrams I
suggest using a special symbol
consisting of two empty states joined
together as a way of indicating that a
state within the state diagram is itself
modeled by another state diagram
then you can draw a second state diagram
for the complex state
I will now summarize what we have
learned by discussing the meaning of
this simple uml State diagram
first the state machine starts in the
initial state
it transitions to the no decimal state
only upon receiving a digit in the range
0 through 9 as input
upon arriving in the no decimal State
the machine depends the received input
digit to the output
the machine stays in this state until
one of three types of input is observed
another digit a period for a decimal
point or the enter key press
if another digit is received the machine
exits then re-enters the no decimal
state upon re-entry the new digit is
appended to the output
if the period key is pressed the machine
exits the no decimal State and enters
the have decimal State appending the
decimal point to the output during the
transition
from the half decimal State the system
will exit and re-enter the have decimal
State whenever the digits 0 through 9
are received appending the received
digit to the output upon the transition
from either State pressing the enter key
ends the Machine by moving to the final
state
also any invalid data to the machine is
ignored at all States since no trigger
is matched
in short this finite State machine
implements logic that reads in and
stores either an integer or a simple
floating Point number in this lecture I
will introduce dynamic memory allocation
at the system level
this method of memory allocation
improves the degree of multi-programming
that A system can provide by allocating
memory to processes as needed instead of
ahead of time in fixed size chunks
yeah
fixed memory partitioning is fast and
efficient in terms of overhead but it
wastes space and limits the number of
concurrent processes to the number of
partitions that will fit into RAM
dynamic memory allocation resolves this
issue by allocating memory to processes
as it is needed
this mechanism increases the degree of
multi-programming with the current
office support but this Improvement
comes at a cost of Greater complexity
in addition there are trade-offs present
in dynamic memory allocation that
directly affect performance of the
system
these issues include efficiency methods
for tracking free space algorithms for
determining where to make the next
allocation and memory fragmentation
the primary issue with dynamic memory
allocation is fragmentation
during execution processes allocate in
free memory in chunks of varying sizes
over Time regions of free space within
memory become non-contiguous with
sections of allocated memory in between
sections of available memory
this fragmentation could lead to Serious
performance issues since program
execution speed will drop dramatically
if every data structure must be
implemented as a linked list of small
pieces
furthermore algorithms that try to
perform on-the-fly memory
defragmentation are extremely complex to
implement and would also severely impact
system performance
since it is Impractical to avoid or fix
fragmentation memory fragments are
significant concern when space is
dynamically allocated
small fragments of memory are useless to
programs particularly CNC plus plus
programs which require structures and
objects to be allocated in contiguous
memory regions
these structures are likely to be in
various sizes that are not efficient to
utilize for memory management purposes
so the systems will allocate a few more
bytes than the structures actually
require in order to improve efficiency
of the memory tracking systems
furthermore structures and objects will
be allocated in freed numerous times
during program execution further
fragmenting the ram
over time fragmentation can waste large
portions of system memory limiting the
degree of multi-programming by making it
impossible for new processes to start
there are two types of fragmentation
external and internal
external fragmentation occurs when free
space and memory is broken into small
pieces
over time as blocks of memory are
allocated and deallocated this type of
fragmentation tends to become worse
external fragmentation is so bad with
some allocation algorithms that for
every n blocks of memory that are
allocated to a process the system wastes
another half in blocks and fragments
with these algorithms up to a third of
system memory becomes unusable
the other type of fragmentation is
called internal fragmentation
internal fragmentation occurs because
memory is normally allocated to
processes in some fixed block size
the block size is normally a power of
two in order to make the kernel memory
tracking structures more efficient
processes tend to request pieces of
memory and sizes that do not fit neatly
into these blocks
thus it is often the case that parts of
a block are wasted as a result
for small memory requests large portions
of the block may be wasted
when a process requests cheap memory the
kernel must find a chunk of free space
large enough to accommodate the request
this chunk cannot be smaller than the
requested size since the process expects
to use all the space it is requesting
since the memory is divided into blocks
for efficiency the chunk of memory
returned to the process is normally
larger than the amount requested unless
the process happens to request a whole
number multiple block size
I'm now going to introduce four
classical algorithms for dynamic memory
allocation best fit worst fit first fit
and next fit
the first classic algorithm for dynamic
memory allocation is the best fed
algorithm
in this algorithm the kernel searches
for the smallest chunk of free space
that is big enough to accommodate the
memory requests
although best fit minimizes internal
fragmentation by avoiding overallocation
external fragmentation is a major
problem
an attempt to reduce the external
fragmentation in the best fit algorithm
is observed in the somewhat
counterintuitive worst fit algorithm
using the worst fit algorithm the kernel
finds and allocates the largest
available chunk of free space provided
it is large enough to accommodate the
request
in theory this allocation strategy
leaves larger and thus potentially more
usable chunks of free space available
in practice however this algorithm still
fragments badly both internally and
externally
aside from the fragmentation both of
these algorithms are impractical in
actual kernel implementations because
they must perform a search of the entire
free list to find the smallest or
largest chunk of memory
the need to search the free list is
eliminated using the first fit or next
fit algorithm
in the first fit algorithm the kernel
simply finds and allocates the first
chunk of memory that is large enough to
satisfy the requests
this approach does result in internal
fragmentation
and it also tends to create small
fragments free space that accumulate at
the start of the free list reducing
performance over time
the next fit algorithm avoids the
external fragment accumulation by
starting the search for the next chunk
of memory from the most recent
allocation
in practice only the first fit algorithm
is used in the Linux kernel and then
only for embedded devices
this algorithm is called the slob
allocator which stands for simple list
of blocks
for non-embedded systems that have the
computational power for a more complex
algorithm slab allocation is used
instead of any of these simple
algorithms in this lecture I continued
the discussion of dynamic memory
allocation
I will introduce the power of two
methods with the buddy system and
coalescence for allocating memory to
processes
then I will introduce slab allocation
which is used within the kernel to
allocate kernel data structures
efficiently
in the previous lecture I introduced the
classic algorithms for memory allocation
best fit worst fit first fit and next
fit
now I want to introduce algorithms that
are actually used within OS kernels to
perform memory allocations efficiently
these algorithms are called power of two
methods and they work by maintaining
information about allocated and free
blocks in a binary tree instead of a
list
at the top level memory is divided into
large blocks called super blocks
as processes request memory these super
blocks are divided into smaller sub
blocks from which the memory is
allocated
sub blocks can be further divided
creating a hierarchy of block sizes
algorithms based on this method are
relatively fast and scaled to multiple
parallel CPU cores these algorithms also
reduce external fragmentation by
coalescing free blocks as I will discuss
in a few moments
some internal fragmentation does still
occur
in this diagram we can see three super
blocks two of which are partially in use
each of the first two super blocks has
been divided into three sub blocks and
the third sub-block of the first Super
block has been further divided
when a process requests memory the
kernel must perform a search of the tree
to find an appropriately sized block to
handle the request in performing the
search the kernel might subdivide an
existing block into a smaller block to
reduce the amount of internal
fragmentation
since this is a search process a
reasonably powerful CPU is required to
make this operation efficient
another Improvement to memory management
is to utilize a buddy system in the
power of two strategy
in this allocation system two limits are
chosen to be powers of two the upper
limit U and the lower limit l
the super blocks are the blocks of size
U and these blocks can be subdivided
into blocks as small as L bytes
there are trade-offs in picking the size
to use for l
a smaller size produces less internal
fragmentation since the block size more
closely matches the smallest request
sizes from the processes
however a smaller size for l means that
there are more total blocks to be
tracked which increases the size of the
binary tree using more RAM to store the
tree and increasing the search time
on the other hand a larger size for L
reduces the search time and makes the
tree smaller but the amount of internal
fragmentation increases
in addition to the block size limits the
buddy system also uses a technique
called coalescence
whenever a process frees a block the
kernel checks to see if either
neighboring blocks is free also
if one or more neighbors or buddy blocks
are free the block is coalesced into a
larger block reducing external
fragmentation the coalescence algorithm
is efficient since the maximum number of
coalescence operations that must be
performed is equal to the base 2
logarithm of U divided by L
by properties of logarithms this value
is equivalent to the base 2 log of U
minus the base J log of L
thus for example a system with a maximum
block size U of 4096 bytes or 2 to the
12. and a minimum block size of 512
bytes or 2 to the 9 will require at most
three coalescence operations to recreate
the super block
returning a single 512 byte block whose
neighboring 512 byte buddy is free will
cause the two blocks to be coalesced
into a single 1024 byte block
if the neighboring 1024 byte block is
free the 2024 byte blocks will be
coalesced into a 2048 byte block
then if a buddy 2048 byte block is free
the third coalescence will produce to
4096 byte super block
the power of two methods are useful for
allocating memory to processes where
some internal fragmentation is
acceptable
however within the kernel it is
preferable to minimize both internal and
external fragmentation to avoid wasting
space
this conservative approach is needed
since the kernel is always mapped into
main memory an efficient solution for
allocating kernel memory is to use a
slab allocation algorithm in which
kernel memory is arranged into fixed
size slabs
each slab is divided into region size
for specific types of Kernel objects
including file descriptors semaphores
process control structures and other
internal data structures
initial layout of these slabs is
performed at compile time
at runtime several of each of the
different slab layouts are pre-allocated
into caches
whenever the kernel requires a new data
structure space for the data structure
is simply taken from the slab cache
if the slab cache starts to run out of
certain Slab layout it automatically
Provisions extras
graphically slabs can be represented in
a manner shown here
in this example we have two
pre-allocated copies of the same Slab
layout in which each slab can hold a
single instance of each of five
different kernel objects
some wasted memory does occur with this
Arrangement since there might be a
larger number one type of object than of
another type of object
however this approach is generally more
efficient in terms of Kernel space
utilization
slab allocation does require more CPU
power than does a classical method such
as first fit thus in some embedded
environments the slab allocator might be
preferable
questions
if slab allocation is chosen over the
slab allocator the Linux kernel has two
choices of slab allocator the first
choice is the original slab allocator
which was the default allocator until
kernel version 2.6.23 this allocator
performed well on shared memory systems
with few CPU cores but wasted
considerable memory space when used on
extremely large shared memory systems
such as those found in graphics
rendering Farms
to reduce the space waste on large-scale
SMA systems Kristoff lameter at silicon
Graphics developed a new allocator
called slub which reduces the size of
data structures needed to track
allocated and free objects
the initial implementation of the slub
allocator contained a performance bug
that affected the results of certain
memory benchmarking tools
initially Kristoff leaped the bug was of
little importance since the conditions
required to trigger it were fairly
uncommon in practice
however Lenas informed Krista that
either the problem would be fixed or
slub would be dropped entirely from the
kernel
in the end it was determined that the
bug was caused by adding partially used
slabs and beginning of a linked list
instead up to the end of that list
the fix was a change to one line of code
and the slub allocator has been the
default Linux allocator this is 2.6.23
in this lecture I will introduce memory
resources and how the system and its
processes view random access memory
in order to run any process or instance
of a program on a computer system we
need to provide two critical resources
access to the CPU and access to random
access memory or RAM for storing and
manipulating data
Ram is a type of dedicated Hardware
memory that is attached to the
motherboard
it is separate from persistent storage
or our disk space
Ram is also volatile which means that it
loses its contents whenever power is
interrupted to the ram modules including
whenever the computer is turned off
at a low level the computer hardware
presents memory to the operating system
as one large block of space
this space is divided into bytes and
each byte in memory has a unique address
that can be used to access it
a 32-bit architecture provides enough of
these byte addresses to utilize up to
four gigabytes of RAM
above that amount there is not enough
space in a 32-bit number to store the
address of any memory locations in
access to four gigabytes thus a 64-bit
architecture is required for systems
with more than four gigabytes of RAM
each process or running instance of a
program on a system uses a different
view of memory
process memory is divided into several
pieces the stack the Heat global
variables and the text segment
the stack is used to store automatic
variables or variables that are local to
functions in the C programming language
space on the heat is manually allocated
and deallocated by the programmer when
writing C code using the function's
Malik and free
space for extra data is located between
the stack and the Heap and the stack and
the Heap grow toward one another
Global variables are provided with their
own section of memory which is allocated
between the Heat and text segment
the text segment is used to store
program code
this segment of memory is read-only and
cannot be changed
as I mentioned in the previous slide
automatic variables are placed onto the
stack
this placement is performed by the
compiler when the program is built
placement of data onto the Heap is
historically performed by the programmer
although many of these operations are
now automated in modern dynamic
languages
in the CNC plus plus languages the
programmer must explicitly request and
release or allocate and de-allocate keep
space
in C these operations are performed
using the Malik and free functions while
the new and delete operators are used in
C plus
in Java the programmer must explicitly
allocate space on the Heap using the new
keyword
however the Java runtime automatically
determines which Heap allocations are no
longer in use and freeze those locations
automatically this process is called
garbage collection
python provides both automatic
allocation and garbage collection
whenever a data structure requires Heap
space the python interpreter allocates
it automatically
once the data structure is no longer
used by the program the garbage
collector deallocates it without
programmer intervention
use of heat memory and processes
presents a challenge to the operating
system because these allocations and
deallocations are not known in advance
the compiler is able to track and Report
the amount of Stack space needed since
the number of local variables in a
function never changes in a language
like C
however the number of Heap allocations
may vary from program execution to
program execution making it impossible
to know exactly how much space should be
allocated in advance
worse keep memory allocations tend to be
small and frequent so the process of
allocating memory from this section
needs to be fast
this speed and dynamic availability
needs to be maintained while the
operating system shares the computer's
Ram among multiple processes at the same
time
in addition to sharing memory among
processes the kernel has memory
requirements of its own
aside from the kernel code and its own
automatic variables the kernel is filled
with data structures that dynamically
grow and shrink during the course of
system operation
these data structures are numerous and
include process control blocks the ready
list scheduling views device access
tables and many other types of structure
unlike some processes however all memory
allocation and deallocation in the
kernel is performed by the kernel
programmers in the Linux kernel
programmers can use one of a number of
functions including K Malik Casey Alec
VM Alec K free and V3
the first issue that must be solved by
the kernel is sharing memory between
itself and a user space process
this sharing is accomplished first by
dividing the memory into two regions
kernel memory and user memory
the kernel keeps its data structures
program code Global variables and
automatic variables in kernel memory
isolating these items from the running
process
process memory is placed in a separate
region from the kernel but the kernel is
always available in memory
this mapping is necessary to maintain
performance whenever an interrupt occurs
the process makes the system call to the
kernel or the process experiences a
fault that must be handled by the kernel
so how do we go about running multiple
processes at the same time
well the first way we can consider which
is used in some types of embedded
systems is to divide the memory into
fixed size chunks called partitions
a memory partition is a single region of
ram that is provided to a single process
both the program code and data
associated with each process must fit
within this pre-allocated space
if a process grows too large it will run
out of memory and crash
furthermore the maximum number of
concurrent processes called the degree
of multi-programming is limited by the
number of partitions available
once all memory partitions are used the
system cannot start any new processes
this situation is exacerbated by the
fact that small processes may not be
using their entire partitions resulting
in wasted memory
in this lecture I will introduce paging
and related topics including logical
addressing address translation and the
translation look aside buffer
paging provides a mechanism for sharing
memory among multiple user space
processes at the same time
this mechanism improves upon simpler
algorithms such as static partitioning
and direct power of two methods by
allocating fixed size pages of memory to
processes
the key to effective memory utilization
with gauging is that each process is
given its own logical memory space
in other words each process has its own
view of memory with its own address
space
the addresses that the process sees are
called logical addresses
these logical addresses are divided into
fixed size pages
each process in the system receives its
own private set of pages with private
memory addresses
when a process accesses memory using one
of its logical addresses the CPU
translates The Logical address into a
physical address
physical addresses refer to locations in
system memory
for performance reasons translation is
done in terms of memory frames or fixed
size regions of ramp
the base frame size is normally four
Kitty bytes although this can vary by
Hardware device and most Hardware can
support multiple different frame sizes
operating systems normally use logical
page sizes that correspond to supported
Arbor frame sizes
again four Kibby byte pages are a
typical base size
on x86 and x8664 systems the Linux
kernel can support so-called huge Pages
which can be as large as one Gibby byte
when using the newest AMD and Intel CPUs
the key advantage to paging is that it
eliminates the issue of external
fragmentation
since the CPU is translating logical
page-based addresses into physical
frame-based addresses anyway there is no
need for the physical frames to be
contiguous
as a result we can store a data
structure and process memory using pages
that are logically contiguous however
when these logical pages are mapped to
physical frames the frames may be
scattered throughout ramp
notice that the distinction between a
page and a frame is a matter of
terminology
a page refers to a block of logical
memory while a frame refers to a block
of physical memory
for now pretend that there is a
one-to-one correspondence between
logical pages and physical frames we'll
make things more complicated later
the key to making page translation
efficient is that the CPU contains
special Hardware called the memory
management unit or mmu which performs
the translation operations
in this diagram the process accesses
memory using logical addresses which are
divided into pages
when requests are made using these
addresses the memory management unit on
the CPU translates The Logical address
into a corresponding physical address
the resulting fiscal address will be to
some point of the physical memory frame
note that individual memory addresses
within Pages or frames still remain
contiguous which is important because
the mmu translates page numbers to frame
numbers leaving the offset to the memory
location within the page unchanged
as shown in this diagram we can divide a
logical address from a process into two
components the page number P and the
offset d
when the mmu is asked to perform a
translation it consults the data
structure called a page table which
provides a mapping between page number
and frame numbers
using this information the mmu
constructs the physical address by using
the corresponding frame number
represented here about the letter F in
place of the page number
once again the offset to the particular
byte within the page or frame is left
unchanged
a particular byte in Ram is actually
addressed using the frame number and
offset into the frame however to the
process this memory access appears to
occur using a logical memory address
which is conceptually divided into a
page number and offset
the offset component is not changed by
the mmu but the page number is replaced
by the physical frame number
in order to perform the translation from
page numbers to frame numbers the mmu
must consult the page table
the page table is a data structure that
is itself stored in Ram in the kernel
memory space
storing the page table in Ram leads to a
major problem since every mmu
translation would require a lookup
since the lookup requires a memory
access each process memory request would
actually require two physical memory
accesses
this situation is especially Troublesome
because a memory access occurs both on
accessing data and upon reading the next
instruction to be executed
without some additional Hardware to
resolve this problem system memory
performance would be effectively cut in
two greatly reducing the overall
performance of the system
the solution for eliminating the double
memory access issue is to add a
component to the CPU called the
translation look aside buffer or tlb
which stores some paged frame mappings
some tlbs also provide room for address
space identifiers which Aid in
implementing memory protection
the tlb is a piece of associative memory
meaning that it can perform rapid
parallel searches resulting in constant
time lookups for page translation
this memory is exceptionally fast
meaning that it is also quite expensive
as a result tlb sizes are typically
limited from eight to four thousand
ninety six entries
the addition of the tlb provides a
potential shortcut for performing
address translation
instead of immediately searching the
page table the mmu first searches the
tlb
if the page to frame mapping can be
found in the tlb then it is used to
perform the translation from page number
P to frame number F this situation is
called a tlb it
a tlb missed occurs whenever the page
number is not present in the tlb in this
case the mmu must search the page table
to locate the appropriate frame number
the CPU and operating system employ
various policies to determine when to
store a page to frame mapping in the tlb
a simple policy would be to use a first
in first out policy that replaces the
earliest entry in the tlb with the
newest entry upon a tlb miss
other more complex and potentially
better policies also exist
in this lecture I will discuss memory
protection including segmentation and
permission bits on page table entries
remember the operating systems perform
two functions abstraction and
arbitration
mechanisms for accessing memory provide
abstractions of the underlying memory
Hardware
however operating systems must also
arbitrate access to Ram by ensuring that
one process cannot access memory that
does not belong to it
without this arbitration a process could
change memory belonging to another
process or worse it could crash the
system by changing memory that belongs
to the kernel
on systems that utilize simple memory
management such as power of two methods
memory access protections are provided
by a mechanism called segmentation
on the majority of modern systems which
employ aging memory protection is
implemented as part of the paging system
and memory access permissions are stored
in the page table
on any system processed memory is
divided into logical pieces or segments
that compile time these segments include
the text segment a region for Global
variables a stack region for automatic
variables and a heap for dynamically
allocated data structures
access permissions apply to each segment
in particular text segment is set to be
read-only
outside a single process there must be a
mechanism to track which segments of
memory belong to which processes
when a process is executing its segments
are marked valid so that it can access
the corresponding memory locations
segments of memory belonging to other
processes are marked invalid and any
attempt to access those segments results
in a fault or interrupt called the
segmentation fault
typically a segmentation fault causes
the process to be terminated
segment memory permissions are
implemented on non-paging systems using
a segment table
the segment table has permission bits
that can be applied to each region of
memory when memory is accessed using
segmentation the segment table must be
consulted to determine whether or not
the access is legal
in this example a process requests
access to memory using a logical address
since we do not have paging with the
system this logical address is not
translated by a page table mechanism
however this logical address is divided
into a segment address and an offset
into the segment in a manner similar to
page translation
the mmu checks the segment table to
determine if a particular memory access
is valid in this example the segment
Table stores up to four permissions and
up to three bits a valid invalid bit a
read write bit and an execute bit
in practice most systems that support
segmentation without paging normally
only use two bits valid and valid and
read write
if the process tries to read from a
segment that is marked valid the memory
access is permitted and occurs normal
the same thing happens if a process
tries to write to a memory location that
is marked both valid and writable
however if a process tries to write to a
segment marked read only or if a process
tries to access an invalid segment the
CPU triggers a segmentation fault and
the process is terminated
for some invalid accesses on a unix-like
system this segmentation fault may be
reported as a bus here
with paging systems which comprise the
majority of modern systems including
mobile devices memory protection is
accomplished by adding permission bits
to the page table entries
in general page table entries will have
a valid invalid bit and a read write bit
the valid invalid bit is used in the
same way as it is for segmentation pages
that a process is allowed to access are
marked valid other pages and any
non-existent pages are marked invalid
if a process attempts to access an
invalid page a CPU fault is raised which
functions like an interrupt to trap into
the kernel
a Linux kernel will send a six Sig V or
sigbus signal to the process depending
on the location and memory the process
tried to access
in practice the signal is normally not
caught and the process terminates
for historical reasons this event is
called the segmentation fault or seg
fault for short
the read write bit used to mark the text
segment of a process can be used to
allow pages of memory to be shared
between processes
pages that are re-entrant or read-only
can be accessed by multiple instances of
multiple programs simultaneously
this capability is useful on Modern
systems since multiple instances of
programs are typically run at the same
time
in the case of a web browser for example
it is only necessary to load one copy of
the browser program code into memory
several copies of the browser can be run
as several different processes sharing
the program code and thus saving memory
the open source Chromium browser and its
Google Chrome derivative allow each tab
to run in a separate process
shared memory Pages allow the code for
the browser any extensions and any
plugins to be loaded only once saving
memory
this diagram illustrates how two
processes can share a single page in Ram
each process sees a handful of valid
frames one of which is marked read only
if this memory frame contains code or
other information that can be shared
between the processes then the two frame
numbers will be identical within the
separate processes
each process may use a different page
number to represent this memory location
however since each process has its own
independent logical view of memory
incidentally this diagram is a
conceptual diagram only it does not
directly map to any particular data
structure in the operating system
instead the two tables illustrate how
each process might see page two
newer AMD and Intel CPUs support an
additional permission bit for setting
execute permissions this bit called the
no execute or NX bit is actually an
inverted permission it is set to 1
whenever execution of data found on a
memory page is forbidden
originally the NX bit was implemented by
AMD on its 64-bit capable processors
using the marketing name of enhanced
virus protection
Intel followed suit and added this
mechanism as the execute disable or XD
bit
the concept behind the bit was to
provide a mechanism that could be used
to prevent execution of native machine
instructions from memory space used for
regular data
although the primary beneficiary of this
feature was a certain virus prone system
that is not a Unix variant Linux kernel
does support the nxbit as a guard
against buffer overflow and similar
exploits
in the example presented in the
hypothetical page table here I'll leave
the page with hex numbers 0 4 A4 allows
code execution
in the event of an exploit attempt a
malicious application could try to load
code at another page perhaps 0 for A1
however since the NX bit is set on that
page any attempt to execute the code
loaded by the exploit will trigger CPU
fault and the process will be terminated
this mechanism increases the security of
the system against certain types of
attacks
in this lecture I will introduce test
driven design
I will Begin by discussing the
importance of testing then I will
introduce unit testing followed by an
overview of the test driven process
ing computer software serves two
purposes
first it provides a way to detect and
isolate buds in the application
any application less trivial than hello
world generally contains multiple bugs
as software matures through its life
cycle we expect the number of bugs in an
application to decrease as issues are
found and fixed although the number of
bugs in an application May decline over
time it is not good practice to release
an initial version of a program with
obvious and or major defects
thus testing should be a major component
of the initial software design process
as well as an ongoing activity
throughout the software life cycle
although we often associate testing with
finding and eliminating bugs in the code
testing serves a second purpose that is
at least as important
that is testing verifies that an
application actually satisfies its
requirements and carries out the
operations it is designed to perform
testing demonstrates that our software
is ultimately correct
in fact one principle of software
development is that a working program as
evidenced by successful testing is a
proof of a solution to some kind of
problem
just as mathematicians use proofs to
verify that steps in solving a problem
are correct we can treat each program as
approved the steps in an algorithm are
correct for solving a problem
I should emphasize here that despite the
recent marketing of mathematical methods
for software analysis in a number of
Professional Publications in our field
testing Remains the one and only way to
verify that a program is ultimately
correct
while mathematical methods such as
formal verification and design by
contract do have useful properties such
as ensuring that our specifications are
not internally inconsistent they do not
replace testing in fact showing that a
mathematical model correctly represents
a solution to a problem is
mathematically equivalent to writing the
correct program
furthermore we have already stated that
a correct program is approved
so how can these tools truly
revolutionize the way we programmed to
the point where programming as we know
it becomes extinct in other words can we
use the formal methods effectively and
efficiently to replace good programming
techniques
well the first problem is that it takes
roughly three times as many symbols to
model a program as it does to implement
the program
as Peregrine Hansen once noted how can
you expect to get the formal approaches
working correctly with three ensembles
if you can't write a correct program
with n symbols the larger issue however
is that all the formal approaches are
effectively applying various algorithms
to the process perhaps these algorithms
could save us some time by figuring out
whether or not our program design will
be correct in advance or to put it
mathematically perhaps these methods
could determine in advance if our proof
will work before we actually do the
proof by writing the program
turns out that David Hilbert had the
same question about mathematical proofs
back in 1928
the question which he called the
insightens problem asked if it is
possible for an algorithm to determine
whether or not a proof would be
successful before actually doing the
proof
within a decade Alan Turing proved that
the halting problem was reducible to the
insurance problem and he also proved the
halting problem is not solvable
algorithmically
thus the answer is no
or to put it succinctly there is no
substitute for testing
there are a number of different ways
that we could test a program and these
methods correspond to different types of
testing
for test driven design we are primarily
concerned with the type of testing
called unit testing
unit testing involves testing each
component of the application in
isolation ensuring that every component
works by itself before trying to
integrate it with other components
in an object-oriented programming
Paradigm a component of the program is
typically a single class
we write unit tests as assertions or
conditions that will be either true or
false we say that a unit test passes
whenever the result of a test matches
its expected result
when a test result does not match its
expected result the test fails
in performing unit testing we normally
use a combination of positive and
negative test cases
positive test cases expect the result to
have a value of true while negative test
cases expect a false answer
we normally automate unit testing by
using some kind of unit testing tool
that runs the test cases for us and
produces a report
a large number of automated unit testing
tools exist
one popular class of unit testing tools
is called X unit these are technically
completely different tools implemented
for testing components written in
completely different languages these
tools tend to operate in a similar way
among the different x-unit tools we have
junit for Java applications Pi unit for
python applications PHP unit for PHP
code in-unit for c-sharp applications
and CPP unit for C plus code
the process of using a test driven
design with unit testing is Illustrated
in this uml activity diagram
this diagram shows a single iteration of
a test driven process
test driven techniques are examples of
iterative and incremental development
models
We Begin by designing a test case which
must initially fail as I will discuss in
a moment if the test case does not
initially fail we continue the design
step until we develop a test case that
does fail
once the test case fails we write code
for the application until the test case
passes when we run the application
against the test case
we run the test as many times as
necessary until the test passes
after the test passes we refactor the
code to make it readable and clean
we then run all the test cases we've
ever written for the system and verify
that all the test cases pass
if not all the test cases pass we still
have work to do on our new code
once all the test cases do pass our
iteration is complete
as I mentioned a moment ago the first
step in an iteration using a test driven
process is to create a test case that
fails
at first this may seem counter-intuitive
why do we want a test case that fails
well remember that we haven't yet
written any code from our test driven
design
if we design a test case that
immediately passes we've made one of two
mistakes
either the test case is wrong
or the program already does whatever the
test is checking
if the test is wrong we need to fix it
so that we don't go to an incorrect test
on the other hand if the test is correct
and the software already passes the test
case then we have no new code to write
since the feature is already present in
the application
once we have a test case that fails we
write code that extends the application
to pass the new test case
this code should be as simple as
possible and it should be written to the
test it should make the application pass
the test nothing more
also this initial code does not need to
be pretty have correct styling except in
python or be especially readable at
first the goal here is to pass the test
once the test passes we refactor the
code to meet Style Guidelines and make
it readable
refactoring means that we change the
code and perhaps the design to make the
implementation cleaner without changing
the functional behavior of the program
we need to ensure that our refactoring
process has not broken The Code by
ensuring that the test case still access
once we finish the refactoring process
we know that the application passes the
new test case
however our new code may have introduced
one or more regressions in the
application meaning that our new code
may have broken something that used to
work
to check for these regressions we must
rerun every single test case that we
have ever written for the application
it is for this reason that it is highly
useful to be able to automate the
testing
if our testing finds no regressions then
our iteration is complete and we can
move on to the next iteration in the
process by designing a new failing test
case for a new feature to be implemented
however if regressions are present we
must fix the regressions
if the code cannot be fixed in a
reasonable time period we revert the
code to the previous version and try the
process again
in other words we throw out the code we
just wrote and try again
while throwing out the code may seem
like a waste it is sometimes faster to
try the implementation again instead of
becoming bogged down and debugging this
economy of speed is especially valued
when using agile methods such as extreme
programming
one final thing to consider about test
driven design is that like any other
development technique it is not the
perfect solution to every problem on the
planet
always be wary of claims that any
process or technique including test
driven design can somehow revolutionize
software development like every other
technique this approach has its
limitations
one limitation is the test driven design
depends upon unit testing and unit
testing has the same power as using
assertions in code
everything we test with the unit test
needs to be reducible to a true false
decision which means that we cannot unit
test some aspects of the system such as
the graphical user interface
another limitation of test driven design
is the same limitation that we have with
software engineering in general
if the specification or high level
design is wrong test driven design
cannot fix it
if you implement a test case using an
incorrect specification that test case
will itself be wrong
writing code that passes an incorrect
test case will Implement a non-feature
and the program will be wrong
finally the test cases must be
maintained over the life of the software
since we need to be able to regression
test after every change
if the test cases are not well written
so that they are themselves maintainable
the test cases may become useless as the
software evolves
should this happen we will lose the
ability to test for regressions and
future changes could easily break the
application
in this lecture I will discuss page
tables
age tables are data structures that
store mappings between logical pages and
process memory and physical frames and
ramp
these structures are used and managed in
different ways on different systems
often with assistance from the hardware
at the end of this lecture I will
discuss extended page tables which are
useful for allowing Hardware to support
multiple simultaneous operating systems
at once
recall from the previous lecture that
the page Table stores mappings between
age numbers and frame numbers
whenever a tlb Miss occurs the page
table must be searched to find the
appropriate mapping
CPUs have differing levels of support
for managing and searching the page
tables automatically on most modern
systems including x8664 and armed CPUs
page tables are managed and searched by
the CPU automatically upon tlbms
this search increases the memory access
time but no fault or interrupt is
generated
as a result the CPU does not have to
perform a context switch
among a few other CPUs the mips
architecture requires the operating
system to manage and search the page
table
whenever a tlb Miss occurs the CPU
triggers a fault which is a type of
interrupt the CPU must make a context
switch away from whatever tasks
currently being executed in order to
execute the interrupt Handler for
default
software managed page tables are
becoming increasingly uncommon even on
embedded systems as the popular arm CPU
supports Hardware management
the mips CPU is typically used in lower
end consumer devices such as inexpensive
e-readers and the least expensive
tablets
one approach to reducing the page table
search time whenever a tlb Miss occurs
is to store the page table as a tree
instead of a list
this technique of hierarchical page
tables divides the page tables into
pages
each logical address in process memory
is divided into an outer page table a
set of offsets into various levels of
subtables and a final offset to the
specific byte of memory to be accessed
this technique can be generalized to any
number of levels in the hierarchy but I
will present here a simple system that
uses only two levels
as Illustrated in this diagram
the data structure is arranged so that
an outer page table provides a mapping
between outer page numbers and Page
table pages
once the proper page table page is
located the translation from page number
to frame number can be completed quickly
since the page of the inner page table
is relatively small
the address translation mechanism used
with hierarchical page tables is more
complex than that used with a simple
linear page table
The Logical address is divided into
additional components
in this example with two levels in the
page table The Logical address is
divided into an outer page table entry
number T which specifies the location in
the outer page table in which to find
the proper inner page table
the next component of the address p is
the offset into the inner page table at
which the mapping can be found
in this example we have a single page to
frame mapping in each inner page table
entry so we can obtain the frame number
from that entry
a real system will be more complex and
likely will require a short linear
search at some level of H2
once the frame number is determined Ram
is accessed in exactly the same way as
it is in simpler designs with the final
address join a frame number and offset
into the physical address
storing the page table in a tree
improves access performance
however as the total amount of system
Ram continues to increase with newer and
newer generations of computers the size
of the page table also increases
moreover the address spaces on 64-bit
architectures are much larger than the
amount of memory that the mmu actually
supports
current 64-bit systems have True
Hardware address sizes in the range of
34 to 48 bits
if we were to store a mapping to handle
every logical page number in such a
system the mapping would be large and
inefficient since the address space is
sparse that is not every 64-bit logical
address can map to a physical location
in Ram since the physical addresses are
at most 48 bits
as a result many of the possible 64-bit
dresses are unused
a solution to this problem which both
reduces page table storage size and
increases search speed is to use a hash
table or dictionary structure to store
the outer page table since several
addresses May hash to the same value
each entry in the hash table is an inner
linear page table which allows the hash
collisions to be resolved through
chaining
translating a logical address to a
physical address with a hashed page
table Begins by hashing the page number
P
ashing is accomplished using a hash
function which may be implemented in
hardware for high performance
the hash value returned by the function
gives the location in the hash table
where the inner page table may be found
a linear search of the inner page table
is performed to locate the frame number
once the frame number f is obtained it
is joined with the offset D to give the
hardware address
Sun architectures notably power PC and
intelitanium store their page tables
backwards
that is the system stores a data
structure with one entry per frame and
the entry stores the corresponding page
number along with the process ID of the
process owning the page
this approach called an inverted page
table is efficient in terms of page
table storage size
however inverted page tables are
inefficient in terms of performance and
these structures are not used on a
majority of systems
a newer x8664 systems with
virtualization extensions Hardware
support exists for extended page tables
or EPT
AMD and Intel each brand this technique
with a different name
AMD uses the term rapid virtualization
indexing or rvi on newer CPUs they used
to call this technique nested page
tables or npt
Intel uses the extended page tables
terminology
EPT adds a level of paging to the system
at the outer level each virtual machine
or guest running on the CPU sees its own
set of memory frames isolated from and
independent of the actual Hardware
the CPU translates page numbers to frame
numbers first by translating the page
number to a guest frame number
the guest frame number is then
translated to a host frame number which
is the physical frame Nook
EPT technology is important for virtual
machine performance since it allows each
guest to manage its own memory
efficiently
moreover guests can access memory
without having to switch the CPU into
hypervisor mode which can be an
expensive operation
the downside to logical address
translation with extended page tables is
that it becomes conceptually more
difficult to understand as illustrated
by the complexity of this diagram
a process running in a guest operating
system makes a memory request just as it
would if no virtualization or present
this memory request is divided into a
page number and an offset as usual
the CPU then performs translation of
this page number P to a frame number F
also as usual
furthermore as far as the guest
operating system is concerned the
translation is complete the guest OS
sees the memory region provided by the
host system as if that memory were
physical memory in other words the guest
OS has no idea that is running in a
virtual machine
to the guest OS the virtual machine
looks just like a physical system
however in reality the guest's physical
memory is actually an illusion provided
by The Host
to make the solution work the host must
translate the frame number F in guest
memory to an actual physical frame
number G
this translation is performed by the CPU
without any context remote switches
using the EPT table
once this translation is performed the
physical memory address is generated by
combining G and D where D is the
original unchanged offset into the page
it is important to note that this entire
process is performed by the CPU without
switching to the host Os or hypervisor
in this lecture I will introduce basic
uml class diagrams
this introduction will be language
independent and will focus on the
diagrams themselves
I will cover language specific uses of
class diagrams in later lectures
uml class diagrams provide a graphical
way to illustrate relationships between
classes and an object-oriented system
they also provide a way to draw an
abstract diagram of a class so that we
can inspect features visually without
having to resort to looking at code
although class diagrams are uml standard
in practice there are differences
between the diagrams produced by
different tools
not all tools support all uml features
some tools add extra features and the
final appearance of diagrams drawn by
different tools varies
certain uml tools are capable of
round-trip engineering which means they
can draw uml-class diagrams from
existing code and generate program code
from uml models
generated code provides templates
classes that programmers can finish
the ability to perform round-trip
engineering depends upon having a
programming language the tool can parse
or upon having a uml class diagram model
in a format the tool can use
the basic entity in the uml class
diagram is a class
Es are represented in the simplest Case
by boxes containing the class name
here we have a sample class named hello
world represented by a rather
underwhelming box
in object-oriented designs the data
members of a class are often called
fields
class fields are listed in a uml diagram
between two horizontal lines under the
class name Inside the Box representing
the class
the first character in the field name
gives the field scope a plus sign for
public scope and a minus sign for
private scope
there are other Scopes which are
represented by other symbols but
remember that different implementation
languages support different scopes
different programming languages also use
different type systems
in the pure case uml class diagrams can
be drawn to be language independent
in practice however most uml class
diagrams have language dependent
semantics which include the type system
used in the target language
in this example the hello world class
has one field
a private member named message which is
of type message with a capital m
the capitalized message refers to
another class named message of which
message with the lowercase m is an
instance
methods or member functions in C plus
speak go below the class fields in the
bottom section of a Class Bus
these methods are functions that are
members of the class which can be called
to operate on instances of objects
static methods or methods that can stand
alone without having to be called from
an instance of a class are underlined
the same scoping and typing conventions
are used for methods as are used for
Fields as with Fields the exact
semantics tend to vary from tool to tool
with each tool using a slightly
different format
in this example we have added five
methods to our class all of them public
we have Setter and getter methods for
the underlying message set message and
get message respectively the class also
has a mechanism to display the messages
using the speak method
two of the methods are special
the first of these is the hello world
method which represents the class
Constructor
the second is the underlined main method
which is a static method that implements
a main driver program for the
object-oriented system
relationships between classes in uml
class diagrams are represented by lines
connecting the classes together
these relationships fall into two
general categories generalization
relationships which show inheritance
between classes and Association
relationships which show how instances
of classes relate to each other
each relationship in a class diagram can
have multiplicity numbers assigned one
or both ends of line connecting the
glasses
multiplicities can consist of a single
number such as the number one or a range
of numbers separated by two dots
if the range is unbounded the second
value after the dots is a star instead
of a number
multiplicity values specify how many
instances of a class are involved in a
relationship
as an example if a relationship between
class is Foo and bar has a multiplicity
of one on the food side and zero dot dot
star or just a single Star by itself on
the bar side
that relationship specifies that for
every single instance of Foo there can
be zero or more instances of bar in the
relationship
as I mentioned before one of the two
categories of relationship in a uml
class diagram is the generalization
which expresses the is a relationship
between classes
this relationship corresponds to
inheritance in an object-oriented
programming language
in this example the simple message is a
type of message in other words the
simple message class is a child class of
the message parent class
this relationship is drawn by connecting
a line from the simple message class to
the message class with a hollow Arrow at
the message end pointing to the parent
class
we leave off multiplicity on this type
of relationship since generalizations
are between classes themselves and not
between instances of classes
the first type of Association
relationship that I will describe is the
aggregation relationship
an aggregation is a weak type of Hazard
relationship between Class instances in
which an instance of one class provides
a collection of instances of other
classes
it is important to note that aggregation
relationships are considered weak Hazard
relationships because the instances that
are collected by the collecting class
can exist independently from the
collecting class
in practice this means that we create
instances of various classes and then
add those instances to the collection
typically with a dedicated method in The
Collector
for example here we have a multi-message
class that acts as a collection of
message instances as indicated by the
relationship with the hollow Diamond at
the multi-message end
multi-message provides a method add
message to add an instance of a message
to the collection
this instance is already created
elsewhere in the code before the add
message method is called to add it to
the collection
if we want a class to contain instances
of other classes without having to
manage collections we can use a
composition relationship
a composition is a Titan Association
that expresses a strong Hazard
relationship between classes
in a composition a class instance
contains one or more instances of
another class and those instances are
created or destroyed by the containing
class
it is important to understand this key
distinction between an aggregation and a
composition
with an aggregation we create instances
to add to the collection then add them
to the collection
for the composition the instances are
normally created in the class
Constructor for the composing class and
destroyed by the destructor of the
composing class
there are no methods to manage the
collection of composed instances
graphically the composition relationship
is represented by a filled Diamond at
the composing instance end of the
relationship as shown in this example
here we have a double message composing
instance that contains two instances of
simple message
as shown by the multiplicity of the
relationship each instance of double
message has exactly two simple message
instances contained within it
these simple message instances will be
created whenever an instance of the
double message class is created and both
simple message instances will be
destroyed with the double message
in this lecture I will begin discussing
virtual memory
due to the complexity of the virtual
memory subsystem the second part of this
introduction will be given as a second
lecture
we have previously seen that each
process in the system can be given its
own logical memory space
this Arrangement allows logical pages to
be mapped to physical frames without the
need for physical frames to be
contiguous eliminating external
fragmentation and increasing the degree
of multi-programming that A system can
support
we can further increase the degree of
multi-programming in a system by
recognizing that processes do not
actually use all the memory in their
logical address spaces at any given time
parts of the program code including
error handlers and infrequently called
functions are not utilized often
furthermore arrays and other data
structures are often oversized and used
in sections instead of all at once
if we can swap unused pages out of
memory and onto a backing store such as
a hard disk we can fit more processes
into memory at once increasing our
degree of multi-programming
furthermore we can give each process its
own large logical memory space which can
in fact be larger than the amount of
physical RAM on the system
when we add a backing store the general
address translation process Remains the
Same
processes Access Memory using logical
addresses which are translated into
physical addresses by the mmu
the page table was still utilized to
store the page-to-frame mappings
however we do add some complexity in
that a frame could be swapped out to
disk at the time when it is needed
the CPU must provide a mechanism to
detect the situation and generate a
fault that the operating system can
handle to bring the required page back
into physical memory
the process of moving Pages or frames of
memory back and forth between RAM and
the backing store is known either as
swapping or as paging
historically the term swapping referred
to the movement of entire logical
address spaces or entire processes
between RAM and disk
moving single Pages or frames of data
between RAM and the disk was called
paging
in modern practice both terms are used
interchangeably in the Linux kernel
component that performs page movements
is called swapper
a single movement of a single page frame
into or out of physical memory is called
a page swap
historically Linux machines use the
dedicated hard disk partition to store
the pages that were swapped out to disk
modern versions of Linux are just as
efficient using a swap file which is a
regular file stored alongside other data
in the file system
it should be noted that swapping is an
optional feature and it is possible and
even quite common to run systems without
any backing store or swapping capability
most embedded Linux systems such as
Android devices do not use a backing
store
if memory cannot be allocated to a
process on such a system the process
typically crashes
now page swaps are implemented by the
operating system
some assistance from Hardware is
required to determine when a page swap
needs to be performed
when translating a page number to a
frame number the mmu checks to see if
the corresponding frame is resident or
loaded in Ram
if the frame is present the memory
access proceeds as normal
if the frame is not present in Ram
however the mmu generates a page fold
which is a CPU exception that is similar
in concept to an interrupt a specific
page fault handling routine is
registered with the system either as
part of the interrupt Vector table or
using a separate structure for fault
handlers
a page fault causes this routine known
as the swapper in Linux to be invoked
it is then the responsibility of the
swapper to locate the missing page on
the backing store and load it into RAM
possibly moving some other page frame to
the backing store in the process
the address translation process gains a
few steps when paging is utilized
a process makes a memory request using a
logical address in its private address
space as usual
the mmu first checks the translation
look aside buffer to determine if the
page to frame mapping is present
in the case of a tlb miss the mmu must
consult the page table to find the
mapping
once the mapping from page number to
frame number is known the mmu must next
verify that the page is actually loaded
in physical RAM
if the corresponding frame is available
in Ram the memory access proceeds as
normal
however if the corresponding frame is
not in memory the mmu generates a page
fault which is essentially a type of
interrupt
if generated the page fault causes the
operating system to switch context to
the page fault handling routine which
retrieves the corresponding memory
contents from the backing store
once this process is complete the OS
changes the CPU context back to the
original process and the memory access
proceeds as normal
in order for the mmu to be able to
detect situations in which your
requested memory frame is not physically
present in Ram an extra bit must be
added to the page table
this bit is set to 1 whenever the
contents of a logical page are present
in a memory frame
if the present bit is zero the page has
been swapped out to the backing store
for efficiency reasons the tlb entry
corresponding to a row in the page table
must also store the present bit
you might have noticed the terminology
between page and frame is starting to
become a bit blurry here
in general we refer to pages of memory
being swapped out to disk even though
the swap operation is actually moving
physical memory frame contents
this fuzzy terminology is a result of
historical evolution of the virtual
memory subsystem
now I'd like to take a moment to discuss
the nature of backing stores as
technology is changing in this area
historically the backing store was a
mechanical hard disk drive and a number
of design decisions in the virtual
memory subsystem still use this
assumption
however many systems now especially
embedded systems have only solid-state
storage
since each block on a solid-state drive
can be erased and written only a finite
number of times there is some question
as to whether it is a good idea to use
an SSD as a backing store for virtual
memory
many embedded devices do not use paging
for this reason
another issue with the backing store is
that it is subject to attack via
forensic disk analysis methods in the
event the device is lost or stolen
sensitive information such as cached
passwords and other credentials might
have been swapped out to the backing
store and these pieces of information
could be recovered
one solution to this problem which is
available as an easy to enable option in
Mac OS 10 is to encrypt the contents of
virtual memory
the downside to this approach is the
addition of CPU overhead on top of the
generally slow nature of the backing
store hardware
another approach to avoiding the issues
of right limits and post-mortem forensic
recovery of sensitive memory data is to
use the Linux compressed caching or comp
cache mechanism as a backing store
with this approach a section of RAM is
reserved ahead of time to create a
compressed Ram disk or zram disk when a
page is swapped out to the cram disk it
is compressed on the fly to fit into a
smaller amount of memory
whenever a page needs to be swapped in
from the backing store the page is read
from the xeram disk and decompressed
although the compression and
decompression steps do result in CPU
overhead the comp cache system is still
generally faster than using a disk or
SSD as a backing store
furthermore comp cache is as secure as
RAM against forensic analysis
particularly against recovering
sensitive information from A system that
has been powered off for a period of
time
in this lecture I'm going to discuss
object-oriented design
the general purpose of object-oriented
design is to increase the modularity of
software by breaking large software
systems into smaller pieces
this approach to software engineering
improves code maintainability by
separating application components from
each other
these components may also be reused in
other software applications
objects in software are modeled after
real-world processes
for example consider the process of
playing a song
in the earliest history of music playing
a song required assembling instruments
and musicians for a live performance
fixed recordings on wire vinyl magnetic
tape and Optical disk made songs
reproducible by a physical machine
with the Advent of digital music this
process is moved to Software
however the basic operations of playing
pausing stopping and moving around the
song remain the same
in an object-oriented design both the
data required to produce the sounds that
comprise the song and the behaviors
required to implement the song listening
process are grouped together in a
logical unit
this logical unit is what we call an
object in a software system
in this case we might call this object a
song player
a common misconception widely held among
students software developers and even
computer science professors is that an
object-oriented language such as C plus
or Java is required to implement an
object-oriented design
this is not the case
object-oriented designs are
theoretically independent of the
implementation language
a traditional procedural language such
as C can be used to implement an
object-oriented program as long as the
programmers are disciplined
of course object-oriented languages do
try to make the implementations of
object-oriented designs easier and less
ugly
that said it is possible to implement a
regular procedural program in an
object-oriented language just Implement
everything in one object
the key concept behind an object is that
it combines a representation of data in
a system along with algorithms to access
manipulate and perform operations on
that data the data are encoded in an
object using properties or fields in the
object
the combination of the values of these
properties is collectively called the
state of the object
an object's behaviors are implemented as
functions that are bound to the object
itself
in object-oriented terminology these
functions are called Methods although C
plus plus retains the older terminology
of member functions methods perform
operations on objects objects are
created in software systems by
instantiating classes
thus another definition of an object is
that an object is an instance of a class
Es are programming language structures
that provide templates that specify how
objects are to be constructed
these classes Define what properties and
behaviors an object will have once it is
instantiated
an issue with dividing a system into
objects is that the developers must
decide how data and behaviors are
divided among objects
the level at which this division occurs
is called granularity and there is a
direct relationship between higher
granularity and the total number of
objects in assistant
achieving the correct amount of
granularity in an object-oriented design
is a balancing act
at the extreme of having too much
granularity the system is comprised of
many small objects
this type of software project becomes
quite complex to develop and rather
difficult to maintain
furthermore due to the nature of the
underlying operations needed to create
manage and Destroy objects the execution
performance of an object-oriented
application will decrease as granularity
increases
at the opposite extreme is an
object-oriented system that is
essentially a procedural application
since all its data and behavior are
implemented in a small number of huge
objects perhaps even a single ginormous
object
this extreme has all the drawbacks of a
non-object-oriented system in that the
code is not modular is more difficult to
debug and is more difficult to maintain
notice that maintenance tends to become
a nightmare at either extreme
a good object oriented design is
somewhere in the middle of these two
extremes
the benefits of object-oriented design
are widely celebrated among different
object-oriented Developers
however no one can ever seem to agree on
a concise set of objectives for an
object-oriented assistant
I have followed the approach of cave
Horseman and Gary Cornell in providing
the objectives of encapsulation
information hiding polymorphism and
reuse
encapsulation simply means the data and
methods operate upon the data are stored
together in an object
these elements are accessed via
well-defined interfaces to the object
information hiding is another desirable
property of an object-oriented system
with information hiding code that uses
an object knows nothing about how the
object Works internally
more importantly other programmers can
be given an interface to an object
without revealing any of the
implementation code preventing them from
using shortcuts or making assumptions
that may later break when the object is
updated
in a sense the object is a black box it
has behaviors but its internal workings
are a mystery to Outsiders
object-oriented designs provide the
opportunity for polymorphic interfaces
this means that different objects can
expose compatible interfaces allowing
them to be used interchangeable
finally well-designed tightly
encapsulated objects can be reused later
either in the same program or in another
application
in theory over time a collection of
well-tested objects will provide a
development team with a library of
useful components that can speed the
development of new applications
in practice of course there is a
downside to any development approach an
object-oriented development is no
exception
developers working on object-oriented
systems have a tendency to run amok with
the design creating a terribly over
engineered mess of code that is
needlessly complex and overly granular
I have been guilty of this design
mistake myself
feature creep and the realization that
more features can be supported with just
a few tweaks are tempting forces
another issue with the theory of
object-oriented design is that objects
may be difficult to reuse in practice
object designs often wind up being tied
to the underlying business process
making reuse difficult in new problem
domains
of course one could argue that if the
objects are designed to be sufficiently
generic they should be more easily
reused
however making the objects too generic
tends to result in the first problem
with the designer and a muck
finally one major disadvantage of
object-oriented designs is that they are
slower to execute than comparable
procedural Solutions
a major cause of this performance
degradation is that objects are
dynamically allocated and deallocated
using heat memory in a process which is
a relatively slow operation
I once saw a software engineer complain
about the fact that the Linux kernel
uses a procedural design with go-to
statements in the code
such as design is a necessity in a
performance critical program like an
operating system kernel an
object-oriented design would simply be
too slow to execute
in this lecture I will discuss the
implementations of object-oriented
designs
by way of example I will present the
same object oriented design in four
different languages Java C plus plus C
and python
I will begin with a reminder about the
distinction between an object-oriented
design and an object-oriented language
it is a common misconception that an
object-oriented language such as C plus
or Java is required to implement an
object-oriented design
this is not the case
object-oriented designs are
theoretically independent of the
implementation language as long as the
programmers are disciplined
object-oriented designs can be
successfully implemented in procedural
languages such as C
the primary benefit to an
object-oriented language is that it
sometimes makes object-oriented
implementations easier
some languages are better at ease of
writing than are others
my design for this example is utterly
simple I have a single class which for
whatever reason I named forward
this class has a single private field
which is a string named message
the design also specifies a single
public method named screen when the
screen method is invoked the message
stored in the class field will be
printed to standard output
for Simplicity this message will be set
to hello world in the class Constructor
note that I have deliberately omitted
Constructor and Destructor methods from
the design since the syntax and
semantics of these methods are tightly
bound to the implementation language
let's begin with the Java language which
is a canonical example of an
object-oriented language
here I have a class named horror which
has a single private field of type
string named message
a public method named screen returns no
value since it is of the Void type
however it does have the side effect of
printing the message stored in the
object to standard output
The Constructor is the final method in
the class with the signature public
horror left brand right paren
this is a special method that runs
whenever new objects are instantiated
using this horror class as a template in
this Example The Constructor sets the
message for each object created from
this class to a value of hello world
I can use or reuse or objects in another
class
here I have a public class named driver
which has a single method named Main
this main method takes an array of
strings corresponding to any command
line arguments to the program
this main method returns no value as
noted by its void type
furthermore main is a static method in
Java meaning that it can be invoked by
itself directly from the class code
without having to create an instance of
the driver class
in other words main is a procedural
function in a language with mandatory
objects
when main executes it instantiates a new
instance of the horror glass creating a
new or object
after this is created main invokes the
screen method on the horror object H
which will cause a message to be printed
to standard output
another example of an object-oriented
language is C plus plus
in this first part of my C plus plus
implementation of the horror class
design I Define the class
since I must manage the allocation and
deallocation of memory for the message
string manually in C plus I have added
both Constructor and Destructor member
functions to the class
C plus plus has a few major problems in
terms of object support
first although data and member functions
are encapsulated together in runtime
object instances the implementation of
the member functions is not encapsulated
inside the class definition as it is
with Java
thus C plus plus requires the use of the
scope operator or the double colons
which I find less easy to read
C plus plus also introduces pointer
notation that is not present in Java
worst C plus plus class definitions
break information hiding by requiring
private members to be disclosed in the
class interface
avoiding this issue requires the
inconvenient use of a void typed pointer
to a private implementation class
unlike Java which is garbage collected C
plus plus requires the programmer to
return dynamically allocated heat memory
to the system manually
thus a Destructor is needed in the class
for this particular example
whenever a new instance of horror is
created The Constructor will allocate a
new string on the Heap containing the
message hello world
if I omit the destructor the memory
containing the string will be leaked
away whenever the horror instance is
deleted
to avoid this memory leak I need to add
a Destructor that deletes the
dynamically allocated string before the
horror instance is deleted
in a more complex object which might
dynamically allocate memory in several
different member functions the
destructor would require careful coding
to ensure that all utilized memory is
returned to the system upon object
deletion
a simple C plus driver program
demonstrating the use of horror objects
is presented here
first I allocate a new horror instance
on the Heap then I invoke the screen
method to print the message to standard
output
finally before I return from the main
function I must remember to delete the
instance I created
to be technical if I failed to call
delete the operating system would
reclaim the Lost memory for me whenever
the program exits
however Reliance on the operating system
to perform such a memory cleanup is
considered bad coding practice
Okay so we've seen that we can Implement
an object-oriented program in an
object-oriented language like Java or C
plus plus
but remember that I previously said that
we can Implement an object-oriented
design using a procedural language
in this example I implement the exact
same object-oriented design using C
it isn't pretty but it is an
object-oriented design
the first step to implementing an
object-oriented design in C is to find a
way to encapsulate the properties of or
data associated with an object along
with the methods that operate on the
object
in C we can use a struct to accomplish
this action
since C does not have true strings my
message will be a pointer to an array of
characters
associating the screen method with
horror objects requires a bit of
trickery
here I am using a c function pointer or
a pointer to a function in the text
segment of the program to allow object
instances to be associated with a
particular C function it will serve as
my object method
this function will not return any data
so the function pointer is given a void
type
since the C function cannot be defined
right here inside the struct I must pass
the instance of the object to the
function as its argument
thus my function will have one parameter
which will be a pointer to an instance
of struct order
since C is not an object-oriented
language it does not have a notion of a
Constructor
however I can use a factory function
instead
a factory function creates a new
instance of an object and returns that
instance
here I have the new horror Factory
function which first allocates a struct
horror data structure on the heat using
the malloc function
next I allocate space for the message
using a predefined constant to determine
how long the message can be
I then use Stir copy to copy the literal
string hello world into the message
field of the new object instance
finally I set the screen function
pointer in the new object instance to
the address of the horror screen
function
this step binds the function or screen
as the new objects screen method
to facilitate reclaiming the Heap memory
which I must do manually since C has no
garbage collection I have added a second
function named delete horror this
function first frees the memory used for
the message then it frees the memory
used for the horror instance itself
note here that order is important I must
free the message memory first before I
destroy the instance
to test my c-based horror code I have a
simple driver implemented as a main
function
my first task inside the driver is to
call my factory function to make a new
instance of Horror then I invoke the
screen method
notice that the screen method invocation
looks a bit strange H Arrow screen left
paren H right parent
in order for scream to have a reference
to the object on which to work I must
pass a pointer to that object as the
first argument to screen
since C is not an object-oriented
language it does not have the built-in
syntax features for automatically
mapping the object on the left side of
the arrow into the method on the right
side of the arrow
the programmer must perform this step
manually with an extra function
parameter
as with C plus plus I must reclaim the
heat memory manually using my delete or
function
if you compare the C code to the
previous C plus code you will notice
quite a few similarities in the steps
required to utilize the horror design
you might also notice that the
implementations are approximately the
same length
if I had to pick a favorite among
object-oriented languages python would
be the winner at least for single
threaded code as you can see from this
complete example which fits on one slide
the python code is exceptionally Compact
and relatively easy to read
the horror class explicitly subclasses
object to create a new style class
instead of a classic class which is a
python-specific issue
class Constructors in Python are always
named Double underscore init double
underscore
notice that the first formal parameter
to any method in a class is always self
which will be a reference to the current
class instance
internally python is operating much like
C and passing the instance as the first
parameter to the method
however unlike C python has syntactic
sugar for accomplishing this task
when I call H dot scream in the driver
code I do not need to pass the instance
to the method explicitly
the other item to note in this
implementation is the double underscore
before the message field name
these underscores are Python's
approximate implementation of private
scope which uses a technique known as
name mangling
another feature of python is that it is
duct typed which means that any two
objects that have the same interface can
be used interchangeably
furthermore since python is background
compiled on the fly as it is executed
the interfaces are not checked until
runtime
thus if I were to reuse my horror class
from the previous slide and add a happy
class with an identical interface but a
different message I could use horror and
happy interchangeably
in my driver code I instantiate an
instance of horror named H in an
instance of happy named I
I then Loop over both objects collected
in a tuple calling the screen method on
each object
this is an ideal example of polymorphism
the same code can be written to work
with two different types of objects
the duct typing used in Python means
that I can distribute my class in
compiled bytecode form along with some
documentation explaining the interface
I thus maintain information hiding
since both the implementation and the
instances are tightly encapsulated
python classes can be easy to reuse
of course nothing is free so there is a
downside which is that python execution
is slower than C in almost all cases
comparison to C plus plus and Java is
more difficult
finally I'd like to demonstrate
procedural programming in a supposedly
object-only language
Java is sometimes criticized for making
it impossible to design
non-object-oriented systems and while
this might technically be true it is not
a practical issue
by implementing an application using a
single class in which each method is
static I can write a procedural Java
program
here I have a static add procedure that
adds two integers together and returns
an integer
in my main method which incidentally is
always static in Java I initialize two
primitive integer variables X and Y
I then call the add function and print
the result the standard output
nowhere in this code do I ever
instantiate any objects with the new
keyword
the system.out object already exists and
is provided by the Java virtual machine
automatically
I can make Java code even more
procedural by removing the main method
and placing my code in a static
initializer block
the only catch to this implementation is
that I must call system.exit at the end
of the block otherwise the Java program
would print my Hello World message then
immediately crash with a no such method
error exception informing me that I have
no main
so to summarize I would like you to come
away from this comparative languages
discussion with an understanding that
object-oriented designs are independent
of the implementation language
you can Implement an object-oriented
design in a procedural language though
it does require a little bit of work and
a lot of discipline
you can also Implement a procedural
program in a mandatory object-oriented
language though you might need to
violate the spirit of the language to do
so
in this lecture I will discuss page
replacement as it is used in the virtual
memory subsystem
I will discuss Global and local page
replacement page table entries that
support page replacement and a number of
classical page replacement algorithms
Whenever there is a demand for memory
that is greater than the actual amount
of physical RAM installed on the system
the operating system must determine
which pages will be kept in memory and
which pages will be swapped out to disk
when memory frame contents are swapped
out to disk the operating system needs
to find a page of memory that is not
currently in use
furthermore in an ideal case the
operating system should also pick a page
that will not be used for some time so
as to reduce the total number of page
swaps
in order for the page swapper to operate
some additional data must be kept about
each page including whether or not the
page has been referenced and whether or
not the page has been altered since it
was last swapped in Durant
decisions regarding page swaps can be
made globally or locally
with global replacement any page in the
system is a potential candidate to be
swapped out in favor of another page
while simpler to implement Global page
replacement does allow processes to
steal memory frames from each other
on the other hand local replacement
policies allocate a limited number of
frames to each process
when a process exceeds its frame
allocation only frames belonging to that
process are selected for replacement
implementing a local page replacement
algorithm is more complex than it seems
on the surface largely due to abelities
anomaly
allocating more frames to a process does
not necessarily reduce the number of
page faults that occur as a result of
that process
in fact with some replacement algorithms
increasing the number of available
frames actually increases the number of
page faults that occur
at the opposite extreme allocation of
too few memory frames to a process also
increases the number of page faults
without enough physical memory processes
will spend more time page faulting or
swapping than they will spend executing
the goal with a local replacement
algorithm is to find an optimal working
set for each process
this working set is the minimum number
of frames that a process actually
requires in order to execute to some
desired level of efficiency
regardless of whether Global or local
replacement policies are chosen the
operating system needs a few pieces of
information to implement page swapping
correctly
first the operating system needs to know
whether or not a page that is currently
in memory has been referenced by a
process
pages that are loaded but unused might
be more ideal candidates to be swapped
out to the backing store
the second piece of information that
needs to be stored in the page table is
the Dirty Bit
this bit is set to one whenever a
process writes to a page which lets the
operating system know that the copy of
the memory frame contents on the backing
store needs to be updated whenever the
page is swapped out
keep in mind that on systems with
Hardware managed page tables such as the
x86 and x8664 platforms the mmu updates
these bits automatically
whenever a page fault occurs the
operating system must locate the desired
page on the backing store then it must
find a free frame and RAM into which the
page can be loaded
if no memory frames are free the
operating system must select a victim
frame to be swapped out to the backing
store
the algorithm that is run to determine
which frame will be the victim is called
the page replacement algorithm
page replacement algorithms ideally
should minimize the total number of page
faults in the running system in order to
maximize system performance
let's take a look at several plastic
page replacement algorithms
the first classical page replacement
algorithm we will consider is the random
algorithm
whenever a page swap is required this
algorithm simply picks a victim frame at
random
in practice this random selection often
picks a page that will be needed in the
near future leading to another page
fault in a short time period
as such it is not effective for
minimizing page faults
another ineffective algorithm is to
select the oldest page or the page that
has been in memory for the longest
period of time
unfortunately this page could be
frequently accessed so if it is swapped
out another page fault could be
triggered in a short period of time to
bring it back into memory
somewhat counter-intuitively selecting
the frame that has been accessed the
least frequently is also ineffective
a page that is used relatively
infrequently might still be used
regularly which would lead to another
page fault to bring this frame back into
RAM
the most frequently used algorithm picks
whichever frame is being used the most
and selects that frame to be swapped out
to the backing store
this is a completely stupid idea since
this page is likely to be accessed again
shortly after it is swapped out
a good algorithm for choosing victim
frames is the least recently used or lru
algorithm this algorithm selects the
victim frame that has not been accessed
for the longest period of time
unfortunately with current Hardware
there is no good way to track the last
memory access time
tracking every access and software would
be a terrible idea since such a scheme
would require an interrupt on every
memory access
thus it is Impractical to implement lru
directly
most implemented page placement
algorithms are approximations of lru
however
theoretically the optimal algorithm or
opt is the best Stage replacement
algorithm to use
with this algorithm the operating system
picks a frame that will not be accessed
for the longest period of time as the
victim delaying a future page fault
related to the corresponding page for as
long as possible
a mathematical proof exists showing that
opt is the best possible page
replacement algorithm
unfortunately opt is also impossible to
implement since it must be able to
predict all memory accesses ahead of
time
as such we are left with lru
approximation algorithms such as the not
used recently or in Ur algorithm
Nur tracks frame accesses using a
combination of the reference bit Dirty
Bit And or an age counter this algorithm
produces reasonable performance in
actual implementations
in this lecture which is presented in
two parts I will begin discussing
processes
I will introduce the process model
discuss the type of information
associated with the process
give an overview of process State and
introduce the concept of process forking
as is usually the case my presentation
is focused on unix-like systems
let's begin by defining what a process
is
a process is an instance of a computer
program in execution
when we ask computer system to run a
program the code for that program is
loaded from disk into memory and
executed as a process in the system
on some platforms processes might be
called jobs or tasks
on a modern system a process consists of
one or more threads of execution
in other words a process can execute one
instruction at a time or it can execute
several instructions at the same time on
the CPU
each process on the system receives its
own private allocation of resources
each process also has access to its own
data and the operating system maintains
statistics about each process in order
to make effective scheduling decisions
foreign
a process is divided into segments
program code and other read-only data
are placed into the text segment
Global variables in a program have their
own data segment that allows both
reading and writing
automatic variables or local variables
and functions are allocated at compile
time and placed on the stack
data structures explicitly allocated at
runtime are placed on the heat
as memory is used by a process the stack
and the Heap grow toward each other
if a process makes use of shared
libraries these libraries are mapped
into process memory between the stack
and the Heat
in order to track processes correctly
and allow multiple processes to share
the same system the operating system
must track some information that is
associated with each process
this information includes the memory
that the process is using as well as the
current location and the process code
that is executing known as the process
program counter
the operating system must also track
other resources in use by a process
including which files are currently open
in any network connections the process
is using
in addition to the information generated
by the process itself the operating
system must keep scheduling information
and statistics about each process
this information includes a unique
identifier or process ID it can be used
to distinguish processes from each other
in order to arbitrate access to system
resources the operating system must also
store information about the owner of a
process so that permissions can be
enforced correctly
to facilitate scheduling decisions the
operating system collects various
statistics about process execution such
as the amount of CPU time consumed and
the amount of memory used
during the lifetime of a process the
process moves between several States
when a process is first created it is
initially in the new state
once creation is complete and the
process is ready to run it transitions
to the ready state where it waits to be
assigned to a CPU or
when the scheduler selects a ready
process to run that process is moved to
the running State and is given CPU
resources
during execution a process might request
external resources such as Disgaea
since these resources take time to
provide the process is moved out of the
running State and into the waiting state
so that the CPU core can be given to
another process
finally when a process is finished it is
placed in the terminated state so that
the operating system can perform cleanup
tasks before destroying the process
instance completely
in this diagram we can see how processes
May transition between states
at creation time a process is placed
into the new state while the operating
system allocates initial memory and
other resources
once creation is complete the process is
submitted to the system and placed in
the ready state
whenever a CPU core is available to
execute a process it is dispatched to
the running state where it executes
execution of a process can be
interrupted for a variety of reasons
if a hardware interrupt occurs the
operating system might have to move the
process off the CPU core in order to
service the interrupt returning the
process to the ready state
or the process might make an i o request
in which case the process is moved to
the waiting State while the system Waits
on the relatively slow i o device to
provide the requested data
once I O is complete the process is
moved back to the ready state so that it
can be scheduled to run again whenever a
CPU core becomes free
upon exiting the process is moved to the
terminated state for cleanup
the mechanism for process creation is
platform dependent
I will be introducing process creation
on a unix-like platform such as Linux or
Mac OS 10.
on these platforms all processes descend
from a single parent process that is
created by the kernel at Bhutan
on Linux this first process is called
init which is the common Unix name for
the first created process
Apple decided to call this process
launch D on Mac OS 10.
by convention the initial process always
has a process ID of 1. the initial
process must also remain alive for the
entire time the system is up and running
otherwise the whole computer crashes
with the kernel panic
the init or launch date process is
started by the kernel at boot time every
other process on the system is a child
of this special process
child processes on Unix are created by
forking a parent process
the parent process makes a system call
named Fork which makes a copy of the
parent process
this copy which is initially a clone of
the parent is called the child process
it is up to the parent process to
determine what if any resources it will
share with the child process
by default the parent process shares any
open file descriptors network
connections and other resources apart
from the CPU and memory with the child
however the program code can close or
reassign resources in the child making
the child completely independent of the
parent
once a child process is forked the child
becomes an independent instance of the
program which can be scheduled to run in
parallel with the parent
however the parent process can be coded
to wait on the child process to finish
executing before the parent proceeds
furthermore the parent process is able
to terminate the child process at any
time
on some systems termination of the
parent process will terminate all child
processes automatically
on other systems child processes become
orphan processes whenever the parent
terminates
unix-like systems including Linux have
the ability to support both models
any process including a child process
has the ability to load a different
program into its memory space
this loading is accomplished via the
exact system call which replaces the
entire program code of the process with
the program code from a different
program
new programs on unix-like systems are
started by forking an existing program
then executing the new program in the
child process
when multiple processes are executing on
the same system they have the ability to
execute independently or share
information between themselves
an independent process is completely
separate from other processes in the
system its execution is not affected by
other processes and it cannot affect
other processes as long as the operating
system is designed and implemented
correctly
alternatively processes could share
information between themselves and
thereby affect each other
when this occurs we say that the
processes are cooperating
cooperating processes may be used for a
variety of reasons including information
sharing implementing high performance
parallel computation
increasing the modularity of a program
implementation or simply for convenience
when implementing certain designs
in part two of this lecture I will
provide additional detail about process
forking and executing new programs
in this lecture I will discuss Process
Management
I will discuss process contexts context
switches and process scheduling
each process running on a system has a
certain amount of information associated
with it
a minimal set of State information that
allows a process to be stopped and later
restarted is called process contexts
process context includes the correct
contents of CPU registers the current
program counter value for the process
and the contents of ram the process is
using
switching between processes on a system
is often called a context switch
although process switch is a more
precise term
the operating system can perform a
context switch from a process into a
section of the kernel and then back to
the same process without actually
performing a process switch
context switches require at least one
mode switch to perform since the CPU
must enter supervisor mode to enter the
kernel
relatively speaking context switches are
a fairly expensive operation and
frequent context switching will reduce
system performance
whenever the operating system needs to
switch from one process to another it
must first make a context switch into
the kernel
the kernel then saves the state of the
previously running process and restores
the state of the process to which it is
switching
a second context switch is then required
to start the newly restored process
on Unix systems processes are created
via the fork system call
following creation the CPU scheduler
determines when and where the process
will be run
once the CPU core is selected the
dispatcher starts the process
whenever a process makes an i o request
a system call into the kernel is made
which removes the process from execution
while waiting for the i o to complete
the process yields any CPU cores it is
currently using
so that another process can use those
resources while the first process Waits
on the relatively slow i o device
operations that cause the process to
yield the CPU cores and wait for some
external event to occur are called
blocking operations
reading data from a file is an example
of such an operation
the process calls the read function and
the read function does not return until
it is read some data
the process may have been moved off the
CPU and then restored and returned to
the CPU while waiting for the read
function to return
some processes are CPU bound which means
they perform large computations with few
i o requests or other blocking
operations
in order to enable the system to service
other processes and effectively
implement multi-programming
CPU scheduler must preempt these types
of processes
preemption involuntarily saves the
process State removes the process from
execution and allows another process to
run
interrupts from Hardware devices may
also preempt running processes in favor
of Kernel interrupt handlers
without this type of preemption the
system would appear to be unresponsive
to user input
now in order to store process State
information the operating system must
maintain data structures about each
process
these structures are called process
control blocks or pcbs
pcbs contain Fields where information
about a process can be saved whenever a
process is moved off the CPU
once again this information includes the
contents of CPU registers and current
program counter value
the operating system stores process
control blocks in linked list structures
within kernel memory space
here is a process control Block in
Greater detail
some of the information Fields include
process State the unique ID for the
process
the process program counter CPU register
contents
memory limits for regions of memory used
by the process
open file descriptors and other data
when performing a process switch it is
critical that the operating system saves
the processes CPU state
at a theoretical minimum this state
information includes the program counter
and CPU register contents
in practice more information will be
saved during each process switch
this diagram presents a simplified view
of process switching where only the
program counter and register contents
are saved and restored
here are the operating system switches
from the process with iodine 1 to the
process with id2
the first step in the process switch is
to perform a mode switch into kernel
mode along with the context switch to
the section of the kernel that handles
process switching
that component of the kernel saves the
program counter and CPU registers into
the process control block for process
one
also the process state for process 1 is
set to ready
indicating that the process is ready to
run again once the CPU core becomes
available
the process switching code then restores
the CPE register contents and program
counter value from the process control
block for process 2.
the state of process 2 is changed from
ready to running
the CPU privilege level is returned to
user mode and context to switch to
process 2.
process 2 now begins executing
during the lifetime of a process the
corresponding process control block is
moved between various queues in the
operating system
each queue is a linked list of process
control blocks and multiple linked lists
overlap
all pcbs are at all times in the job
queue which is a linked list of all
process control blocks in the system
process control blocks corresponding to
processes in the ready state are linked
into the ready list
processes waiting for device i o have
their pcbs linked into various different
device queues
in this diagram we can see the pcbs for
five different processes
all pcbs are members of the job list
with list links depicted by the green
arrows
three jobs are in the ready list and two
jobs are in a device queue waiting on i
o
linked lists within each queue are
represented by the dark blue arrows
notice that the two linked lists for the
queues overlap the linked list for the
job list
careful management of linked lists is a
major requirement of operating system
kernel code
now I'd like to shift Focus for a moment
to mention scheduling since it is
closely related to the linked list
management
in operating systems theory we typically
divide scheduling into three types job
scheduling midterm scheduling and CPU
scheduling
job or long-term scheduling refers to
the selection of processes to place into
the ready state
this type of scheduler has a long
interval typically on the order of
seconds to minutes
one of the clearest examples of job
scheduling on Modern systems occurs on
high performance computational clusters
on which users submit jobs that may
require hours to be scheduled and
execute
midterm scheduling refers to the
swapping of inactive processes out to
disk and restoring swapped processes
from disk
many of these tasks are now part of the
virtual memory subsystem
CPU scheduling or short-term scheduling
refers to the selection of processes
from the ready list to run on CPU cores
this type of scheduling will be the
subject to Future lectures
one important operating system component
related to short-term scheduling is the
dispatcher which receives a process
control block from the short-term
scheduler and restores the context of
the process
the dispatcher also completes the
context switch to the process by
performing a mode switch into user mode
and jumping to the instruction address
specified by the newly restored program
counter
thanks for watching please subscribe and
don't miss out on new videos and
lectures